<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-18T15:07:26+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ordina JWorks Tech Blog</title><subtitle>We build innovative solutions with Java and JavaScript. To support this mission, we have several Competence Centers. From within those Competence Centers, we provide coaching to the employee and expert advice towards our customer. In order to keep in sync with the latest technologies and the latest trends, we frequently visit conferences around the globe.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Accelerating your slow Java Lambda with AWS Lambda SnapStart</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2023/01/13/aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accelerating your slow Java Lambda with AWS Lambda SnapStart" /><published>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2023/01/13/aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2023/01/13/aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function.html"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#what-is-snapstart">What is SnapStart?</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#versions">Versions</a></li>
      <li><a href="#pricing">Pricing</a></li>
      <li><a href="#limitations">Limitations</a>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="#uniqueness">Uniqueness</a></li>
          <li><a href="#networking">Networking</a></li>
          <li><a href="#ephemeral-data">Ephemeral data</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#using-snapstart">Using SnapStart</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>If you use <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/lambda/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AWS Lambda</a> in combination with Java runtimes, you will notice (or probably have already noticed) that one of the main setbacks is the cold start time.
A cold start refers to the process where a Lambda is invoked for the first time and the Lambda has to be initialized.
AWS needs to create a new function instance and spin it up with every <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/lambda-runtime-environment.html#runtimes-lifecycle-ib" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">initialization</a>.</p>

<p>Depending on your environment and application size, it can take up to 10 seconds to complete the init phase.
Especially when using frameworks such as Spring Boot where features like dependency injection and component scanning can take a lot of time to initialize.
This is a delay that most want to avoid as it significantly slows down your application flow in some situations.
<strong>Do mind</strong> that this is only during the init phase; once the Lambda instance is running, the cold start process is over until the next time your Lambda needs to be instantiated again.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-12-23-aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function/lambda-execution-lifecycle.png" alt="Lambda execution lifecycle" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
<em>Lambda execution environment lifecycle - without SnapStart - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dnFm6MlPnco" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Best practices of advanced serverless developers (AWS re:Invent 2021)</a></em></p>

<p>AWS has always recognized the problem and now comes with a solution called <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/snapstart.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lambda SnapStart</a>.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-snapstart">What is SnapStart?</h2>
<p>Introduced at AWS re:Invent 2022, AWS <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/snapstart.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lambda SnapStart</a> is the newest feature to eliminate the cold start problem by initializing the function when you publish a new version of a Lambda.
It takes a snapshot, through <a href="https://firecracker-microvm.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Firecracker</a> which AWS uses to run Lambda and Fargate, encrypts and caches it so it can be instantly accessed whenever it is required.
When a Lambda is invoked and needs to set up a new instance, it will simply use the cached snapshot, which greatly improves startup times (officially up to 10x).</p>

<h3 id="versions">Versions</h3>
<p>By default, SnapStart is disabled.
You can enable it, but only for published Lambda versions.
This means that it only works for versions that are published on the AWS account and that it is not implemented on the $LATEST tag. If you want to make use of Lambda SnapStart, be sure to do so on a published version.
The snapshot of your Lambda is created upon the version publishing process.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-12-23-aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function/snapstart-overview.png" alt="SnapStart overview" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
<em>SnapStart overview - snapshot gets created during version publishing - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZbnAithBNYY" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AWS Lambda SnapStart (AWS re:Invent 2022)</a></em></p>

<h3 id="pricing">Pricing</h3>
<p>The SnapStart feature comes with AWS Lambda and has no additional pricing.</p>

<h3 id="limitations">Limitations</h3>
<p>While SnapStart is a great feature and can save time in Lambda cold starts, it also comes with its limitations.
SnapStart currently does not support the following features and services:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/provisioned-concurrency.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">provisioned concurrency</a></li>
  <li>arm64 architecture</li>
  <li>the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/runtimes-extensions-api.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lambda Extensions API</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/efs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EFS</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/xray/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">X-Ray</a></li>
  <li>Ephemeral storage up to 512 MB</li>
  <li>Limited to Java 11 runtime</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="uniqueness">Uniqueness</h4>
<p>SnapStart always requires your snapshot to be unique. 
This means that if you have initialization code that generates unique content, it might not always be unique in the snapshot once it is restored in other Lambda invocations.
The goal is to generate this content after the initialization process, so it is not part of the snapshot.
Luckily, AWS has provided a <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/snapstart-uniqueness.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">documentation page</a> in which they provide best practices on how to tackle that problem.
They even came up with a <a href="https://github.com/aws/aws-lambda-snapstart-java-rules" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SpotBugs plugin</a> which finds potential issues in your code that could prevent SnapStart from working correctly.</p>

<h4 id="networking">Networking</h4>
<p>Network connections are not being shared across different environments.
Thus, if network connections (for example, to other AWS services such as an RDS or SQS) are instantiated in the initialization phase, they will not be shared and will most likely fail when the snapshot is being used later again.
Although most popular frameworks have automatic database connection retries, it is worth the time to make sure that it works correctly.</p>

<h4 id="ephemeral-data">Ephemeral data</h4>
<p>Data that is fetched or temporary (for example a password or secret) should be fetched after the initialization phase.
Otherwise, it will save the secret in the snapshot, meaning that authentication failures (and security risks) might occur once the initial secret value has expired or has been changed.</p>

<h2 id="using-snapstart">Using SnapStart</h2>
<p>To investigate the improvement in cold start execution time when using AWS Lambda SnapStart, we wrote a simple Lambda function in Java 11 using <a href="https://spring.io/projects/spring-cloud-function" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Spring Cloud Function</a>.
This Lambda function, when invoked, will retrieve some JSON data from a <a href="https://dummyjson.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">dummy REST API</a> and return it to the user.
The code can be found on <a href="https://github.com/ordina-jworks/aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-boot" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Github</a>.</p>

<p>We made use of the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/serverless-application-model/latest/developerguide/what-is-sam.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AWS Serverless Application Model (SAM)</a> to build our Lambda function and deploy it to AWS.
Enabling the SnapStart feature can be easily done by adding the following two lines to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Properties</code> section of the Lambda function resource in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">template.yaml</code> file used by AWS SAM:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>SnapStart:
  ApplyOn: PublishedVersions
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>We started by invoking our Lambda function’s unpublished version ($LATEST), in which case SnapStart is not used, and received the following summary from AWS:</p>

<p><img src="/img/2022-12-23-aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function/lambda-cold-start.png" alt="Summary lambda without SnapStart" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>We can observe an <strong>Init duration</strong> of around 2.7s, i.e. the time that is spent initializing the execution environment for our Lambda function.</p>

<p>Next, we manually published a new version of our Lambda function using the AWS Console.
This can be done by navigating to the <em>Versions</em> tab of our Lamdba function and pressing the <em>Publish new version</em> button.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-12-23-aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function/lambda-versions.png" alt="Lambda function verions" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
<em>Versions tab listing all published versions of a Lambda function.</em></p>

<p>Invoking this newly published version provides us with the following summary:</p>

<p><img src="/img/2022-12-23-aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function/lambda-snapstart.png" alt="Summary lambda with SnapStart" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>In this case, we can see SnapStart is used.
The initialization of the execution environment, represented by the <strong>Init duration</strong> we saw earlier, now happens when publishing the new version.
Only the restoration of the snapshot, represented by the <strong>Restore duration</strong>, is performed now.</p>

<p>It is quite clear that using Lambda SnapStart is advantageous in most cases.
We managed to decrease the cold start execution time of our Lambda function from almost 5s (<strong>Init duration</strong> + <strong>Duration</strong>) to around 2.6s (<strong>Restore duration</strong> + <strong>Duration</strong>), just by enabling this feature.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>SnapStart is a great feature and can save a lot of time in your application flow.
It’s a feature that should have been present already as it comes a bit too late. 
But now that it is here, Java developers should take measures in order to implement this as it can save a lot of time in cold-starting their Java Lambdas.
We would have liked to see it implemented by default when you create a version, but sadly, this is not the case (yet).
It comes only for Java, which is understandable as Java Lambdas face this obstacle the most. 
Still, we certainly won’t be surprised if AWS decides to release this feature for other languages and/or frameworks.</p>

<p>Altogether we can definitely recommend using this new feature for your Java Lambdas.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Yolan&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Vloeberghs&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;yolan-vloeberghs-23825aa3&quot;, &quot;github&quot;=&gt;&quot;yolanv&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/yolan-vloeberghs/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;yolan-vloeberghs.jpg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Java Consultant&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;yolan.vloeberghs@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Yolan Vloeberghs is a Java and Cloud engineer with a sharpened focus on all things related to cloud, specifically AWS. He loves to play around with various technologies and frameworks and is very passionated and eager to learn about everything related to cloud-native development.&quot;}</name><email>yolan.vloeberghs@ordina.be</email></author><category term="Cloud" /><category term="aws" /><category term="lambda" /><category term="snapstart" /><category term="cloud" /><category term="spring" /><category term="java" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction What is SnapStart? Versions Pricing Limitations Uniqueness Networking Ephemeral data Using SnapStart Conclusion]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2023-01-13-aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function/header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2023-01-13-aws-lambda-snapstart-spring-cloud-function/header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Keeping up with dependencies like a boss</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/10/27/renovate.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keeping up with dependencies like a boss" /><published>2022-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/10/27/renovate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/10/27/renovate.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Anything worth doing twice is worth automation.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#whats-the-problem">What’s the problem?</a></li>
  <li><a href="#what-is-mend-renovate">What is Mend Renovate?</a></li>
  <li><a href="#behind-the-curtains">Behind the curtains</a></li>
  <li><a href="#how-to-setup">How to setup</a></li>
  <li><a href="#tips-and-tricks">Tips and tricks</a></li>
  <li><a href="#why-should-i-use-it">Why should I use it?</a></li>
  <li><a href="#links">Links</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="whats-the-problem">What’s the problem?</h2>

<h3 id="lack-of-features">Lack of features</h3>

<p>Let’s imagine you need to implement support for a new feature.
Let’s imagine that that feature is super easy to implement due to almost native support for the functionality in a library you’re already using. 
That sounds like a great day, right? 
You add the code to glue together the API and the library, perform some tests and call it a day. 
There is just one problem, you didn’t check which version of the dependency you were using and the feature you need is only supported in versions 8.x.x and beyond. 
You check your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pom.xml</code>, only to figure out that you’re on version <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">6.8.21</code>.
Now you have two options, refactor 25% of your codebase to be able to use the new library or 5x your effort for implementing the feature without the support of the library.
That doesn’t sound like a great day at the (home-)office, now does it?</p>

<p>Wouldn’t be great to have been on version <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">8.1.2</code> already?</p>

<h3 id="dependent-systems">Dependent systems</h3>

<p>Let’s imagine another scenario.
You’re using a library to connect to an Elasticsearch cluster that’s provided by another team. 
Your application is running nicely in production and you’re steadily adding features to the codebase.
The end of the year approaches and with that, the pressure to deliver the final set of promised features increases.
All of a sudden, your application starts throwing all kinds of errors in your development environment. 
After some stressful debugging, you figure out that the Elasticsearch cluster has been upgraded to the latest version by the other team. 
Furiously, you open up your mailbox and look for an email about the upgrade. 
Of course, you find the email dating back four weeks where the team announced that they will start upgrading this week for development and do production in two weeks.</p>

<p>Since it’s a shared system, you can’t fault the other team, nor can you halt their upgrade path. 
So the only way forward is to upgrade the library. 
You open up your <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pom.xml</code> file only to discover that you’re already 2 major versions behind. 
Upgrading will take ages since your code depends on previously deprecated and by now removed API support.</p>

<p>That sounds like a lot of overtime, stress and/or missed deadlines for the end of the year, doesn’t it…</p>

<h3 id="security-vulnerability">Security Vulnerability</h3>

<p>Now we get to a scenario that maybe 50% of the Java community experienced at the end of 2021.
A severe security vulnerability was discovered in a very popular logging library: Log4J. 
Normally, vulnerabilities aren’t this severe and there aren’t part of the nine o’clock news.
Now imagine that you are using a vulnerable software component and you aren’t informed by the news that you need to urgently update, how would you know about the vulnerability? 
Maybe you have some scanning software that checks for know CVEs?
Maybe you have really good developers that are subscribed to the mailing lists of all dependencies they’re using?
Or more likely than not, you just don’t know you’re vulnerable. 
OWASP identified <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Vulnerable and outdated components</code> as number six on their <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Top 10 Web Application Security Risks</code> of 2021.</p>

<p>Wouldn’t it have been nice to have a PR on every repository that had the Log4J dependency with the new version updated? 
So that you only had to merge that PR to mitigate the vulnerability?</p>

<h2 id="what-is-mend-renovate">What is Mend Renovate?</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.mend.io/free-developer-tools/renovate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mend Renovate</a> (formerly known as WhiteSource Renovate) is a tool that detects dependencies in your code and informs you about new versions of your dependencies.
It’s a free (at the time of writing) tool that can be used as a GitHub App or as a self-hosted tool. 
Renovate scans a repository and detects the used dependencies, relying on dependency managers.
As of time of writing, Renovate supports about <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/modules/manager/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">80 different dependency management</a> systems out of the box.
Next, it can integrate with your code repositories (e.g. Bitbucket, Github, Gitlab, …) and automatically update the dependency in your code. 
It can create pull requests (PR) for every update it detects and even adds changelog (if available) information to the PR. 
This is especially helpful if there are (manual) changes required to use the new version of the dependency.
So Renovate can <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">detect</code> your dependencies, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">inform</code> you about the updates and even tell you <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">how</code> to update.</p>

<h2 id="behind-the-curtains">Behind the curtains</h2>

<p>Now, how does this magic work?</p>

<p>Renovate starts by scanning your source code for dependencies.
It does this by looking for dependency files in your repository, let’s take the file structure below as an example.</p>

<div class="language-bash highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>repo/ 
├─ src/ 
├─ Dockerfile 
├─ pom.xml
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Renovate will detect the Dockerfile and the Maven dependency file (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pom.xml</code>).
It will pass these files to the dependency managers internally and detect which dependencies are being used.
Let’s imagine that the Dockerfile has the following <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">FROM</code> line at the top: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">FROM amazoncorretto:18.0.0</code>
The dependency manager for docker will detect that this is the repository <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">amazoncorretto</code> with tag <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">18.0.0</code> on Docker Hub.
Next, it will look in the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pom.xml</code>.</p>

<p>Excerpt of the pom.xml:</p>
<div class="language-xml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;dependency&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;groupId&gt;</span>org.apache.logging.log4j<span class="nt">&lt;/groupId&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;artifactId&gt;</span>log4j-core<span class="nt">&lt;/artifactId&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;version&gt;</span>2.12.2<span class="nt">&lt;/version&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/dependency&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p><strong>Note: Never use this dependency! This is a vulnerable version of log4j-core.</strong></p>

<p>Renovate will detect the following Maven dependency: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">org.apache.logging.log4j:log4j-core:2.12.2</code></p>

<p>Next, Renovate will check for new versions of those dependencies. 
By default, Renovate will use the central Apache Maven Repository to check for newer versions of Maven dependencies. 
For Docker images, Docker Hub is used by default.
Like almost everything in Renovate, you can configure it to use different data sources, like your own Nexus, Artifactory or AWS Elastic Container Registry for example.
This way you can limit what sources are considered and you can also use Renovate to update internal dependencies instead of just public ones.</p>

<p>Now let’s imagine that the most recent version of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">amazoncorretto</code> image is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">18.0.2</code> (This is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">latest</code> at the time of writing).
Renovate will create a branch from your main branch, update the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">FROM</code> entry in your Dockerfile and push the changes into your repository as a new branch. 
Now your regular CI/CD process can be followed to build, test, merge and deploy your component with the updated dependency.</p>

<p>The same scenario, with a second branch, will be performed to update the log4j dependency.</p>

<p>As an additional bonus, if the dependency exposes it, Renovate will add the changelogs in the pull/merge request it creates in your repository.
This makes it visible if any breaking changes were introduced and allows you to easily check, together with your tests, if you need to make changes to your code to update the dependency.</p>

<p>Example of changelogs embedded in PR.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/20221009-renovate/pr-changelog.png" alt="PR with changelogs" class="image center" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<h2 id="how-to-setup">How to setup</h2>

<p>How to use Renovate depends a bit on where your code lives.</p>

<h3 id="renovate-github-app">Renovate GitHub App</h3>

<p>If you’re using GitHub, the setup is as easy as enabling the <a href="https://github.com/apps/renovate" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub Renovate app</a> for your repository. 
Next, Renovate will create an onboarding pull request where it will suggest a default Renovate configuration, show a preview of what dependencies it detected and an example of what updates it has found. 
The only thing left is to merge the pull request and renovate will automatically start scanning your repository and start creating branches and pull requests with dependency updates.</p>

<h3 id="self-hosted-renovate">Self-hosted Renovate</h3>

<p>The second option is to host Renovate yourself.
This option also comes with a lot more configuration capabilities, especially w.r.t. private data sources. 
You can run Renovate <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/examples/self-hosting/#gitlab-cicd-pipeline" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">as (part of) a pipeline</a>, as a <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/examples/self-hosting/#docker" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Docker container</a> or even as a <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/examples/self-hosting/#kubernetes" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CronJob on Kubernetes</a>.
Since you only need NodeJS/NPM to be available, you can run it almost anywhere you want. 
You can find an example of how to run Renovate as a Cronjob on a Kubernetes cluster in <a href="https://github.com/pietervincken/renovate-tekton-argo-talk/tree/main/k8s/renovate" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this repository</a>.</p>

<p>With the self-hosted deployment method, you need to either explicitly tell Renovate which repositories it needs to consider or configure it to auto-detect repositories based on the access of its user or the integration with your code repositories.
For Bitbucket Server you can for example configure Renovate to automatically discover all repositories in a specific project.
This prevents you from having to make changes to the Renovate configuration every time a new repository gets added.</p>

<p>In this scenario, you’ll have to provide Renovate an identity to interact with the code repositories as well, as it needs to be able to create branches and push code changes.</p>

<h2 id="tips-and-tricks">Tips and tricks</h2>

<p>Aka things we discovered and/or went wrong while we started using Renovate.</p>

<h3 id="limit-concurrent-branches--prs">Limit concurrent branches / PRs</h3>

<p>An important tip, especially if your repository contains quite some outdated components, is to limit the number of concurrent branches and pull requests that Renovate is allowed to create. 
By default, Renovate is not limited to a specific number which might result in literally 10s if not over 100 pull requests being created. 
To prevent you and/or your developers from becoming overwhelmed by this, <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/configuration-options/#prconcurrentlimit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">limiting the concurrent pull requests</a> is a must!</p>

<h3 id="setup-auto-merging">Setup auto-merging</h3>

<p>Auto-merging is a very powerful feature in Renovate, especially in combination with very good automated tests and continuous integration practices. 
<strong>Don’t</strong> enable this when starting with Renovate. 
Over time, you’ll be able to identify repositories and data sources for which updates are becoming as easy as just accepting the PRs. 
For these combinations of repositories and data sources, you can enable auto-merging in Renovate. 
This means that Renovate will perform the update to the code repository and if the result of the pipeline for that change is green, it will attempt to merge that PR.
If you have a well-automated CI/CD process, this can allow Renovate to automatically update your dependencies and make sure that your software automatically has the latest dependencies.</p>

<h3 id="use-it-in-deployment-repositories">Use it in deployment repositories</h3>

<p>The term dependency is interpreted quite broadly in Renovate. 
Not only classical libraries and Docker base images can be detected. (aka build phase dependencies)
It can also detect dependencies in your deployment setups. 
This means that it can detect updates in <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/modules/manager/ansible/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ansible playbooks</a>, update <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/modules/manager/helmv3/https://docs.renovatebot.com/modules/manager/helmv3/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Helm Chart</a> references, update <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/modules/manager/kubernetes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kubernetes manifests</a> (including the API versions as shown below!) and even <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/modules/manager/kustomize/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kustomize</a> and <a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/modules/manager/terraform/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Terraform</a> setups.</p>

<p>Enabling automated dependency management for those deployment repositories can greatly reduce the amount of effort that is required to update a newer external dependency. 
It also helps to make sure that an update is rolled out consistently across many different environments. 
Especially in a larger corporate context, it can be hard to determine what the latest version of a specific service is and on which environments it’s running or not. 
By enabling Renovate to detect the dependencies, it can easily inform the different teams/users of newer versions.</p>

<p>Example of automated Kubernetes API updates.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/20221009-renovate/k8s-api-update.jpg" alt="Kubernetes API updates" class="image center" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<h3 id="start-slow">Start slow!</h3>

<p>The last tip might sound a bit contradictory, but starting small with Renovate is key. 
You want to build confidence in the data sources you’re using and prevent your teams from being overwhelmed by Renovate PRs. 
A good way to start with Renovate is to enable it on just one or maybe a handful of low-impact repositories. 
This way, you can see what effect it has on your workflow and how teams react to having these PRs pop up in their change feed.</p>

<h2 id="why-should-i-use-it">Why should I use it?</h2>

<p>At the start of this blog post, we’ve discussed why updating dependencies is important.
As discussed, bulk updating dependencies is an option, but it might be time-consuming and therefore might be bumped to the bottom of the priority list.
Not to mention that you might miss important security updates if you need to “look” for the changes manually. 
Automating the update process and allowing a tool to automatically discover the updates, makes the update process a lot simpler and faster. 
If you already have a good CI/CD process that allows you to build, test, merge and deploy small changes easily, Renovate will save you tons of time and prevent you from running unsafe, outdated software.</p>

<p>And as one of my favorite sayings goes: <strong>anything worth doing twice is worth automating</strong></p>

<h3 id="links">Links</h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.mend.io/free-developer-tools/renovate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mend Renovate website</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/renovatebot/renovate" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Renovate Github Repository</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.renovatebot.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Renovate docs</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://youtu.be/fAEbRmD4-G0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">JOIN 2022 Talk YouTube Link</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/pietervincken/renovate-tekton-argo-talk/tree/main/k8s/renovate" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sample Renovate Setup</a></li>
</ul>

<p>This blog post is a companion to a talk at the JOIN 2022 conference.</p>

<p>Feel free to reach out to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pieter-vincken-a94b5153/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">me</a> if you want to look into this solution.</p>

<p>Special thanks to the Unicorn team for helping with the blog post and automating the dependency updates!</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Pieter&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Vincken&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;pieter-vincken-a94b5153&quot;, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;PieterVincken&quot;, &quot;github&quot;=&gt;&quot;pietervincken&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/pieter_vincken/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;pieter-vincken.jpeg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Cloud Automation Engineer&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;pieter.vincken@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Pieter Vincken is a Cloud Automation Engineer with a strong interest in anything related to Cloud Native. He likes to optimize development workflows, from Ideation until code running in production, by enabling CI/CD to be fully automated. Any solutions he creates, will have started as an architectural drawing.&quot;}</name><email>pieter.vincken@ordina.be</email></author><category term="Cloud" /><category term="cloud" /><category term="automation" /><category term="cicd" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Anything worth doing twice is worth automation.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/20221009-renovate/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/20221009-renovate/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ode to JOIN</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/architecture/2022/10/24/ode-to-join.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ode to JOIN" /><published>2022-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/architecture/2022/10/24/ode-to-join</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/architecture/2022/10/24/ode-to-join.html"><![CDATA[<p>We had JOIN, we had fun, we had seasons in the sun. 
It has already been a month since the 9th edition of the JOIN conference was concluded. 
And even though it had been ten years since the first edition, the skipped year due to the pandemic will cause us to have an additional anniversary edition next year. 
The aluminum edition will be a sight to see, and it would be a shame to miss it.</p>

<p>As for this edition, the stakes were high with a new team taking over the reins of those who had come before them. 
As a member of this new team, I had the pleasure to rise to the occasion and make sure the legacy stayed untarnished. 
The new team did not disappoint, and even though there were minor hiccups during the day, in the end, the conclusion was clear. 
A job well done, and a crowd that had gotten a day’s worth of interesting talks topped off with a barbecue blessed with early autumn sun.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-10-24-ode-to-join/JOIN-01.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
Pieter Van den Wyngaert Opening the Conference in Style</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-10-24-ode-to-join/JOIN-02.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
Getting the inside scoop from our friends at AWS</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-10-24-ode-to-join/JOIN-03.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
Getting to Know your Fellow Conference Goers</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-10-24-ode-to-join/JOIN-04.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
Getting in Touch with the Serverless World (courtesy of November Five)</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-10-24-ode-to-join/JOIN-05.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
Ending the Conference by Queueing up for the Barbecue Diner</p>

<p>Not only did we have a new team, but the founding member of the conference, the jWorks unit or Ordina was joined by their colleagues from the BOLD unit to make it an even more impressive package deal. 
The talks reflected this, not only in a healthy mix of speakers but also in a healthy mix of topics ranging from the concerns about patching 3rd party software to the accessibility concerns of digital products for disabled people. 
We had people from AWS talking about the various ways to modernize applications, and we had people from Flowable showing process automation at its finest. 
On the subject of Flutter, experts came various insights into the world of mobile app design, and even the mysteries of the design system were laid bare for all to understand.</p>

<p>Even though the topics were varied, the main theme was clear: Software development for the current times, leveraged by the possibilities that are present in the Cloud and the options we have for multi-channel approaches toward the customer. 
Thinking back to the Nexus of Force that Gartner used to taut: Social, Mobile, Analytics, and Cloud, the talks covered three of these four topics. 
Not a bad score for a conference that only lasts a single day.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-10-24-ode-to-join/SMAC.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" />
Taken from the <a href="https://blogs.gartner.com/mark-mcdonald/2022/08/15/relevance-is-customer-and-situationally-specific/smac/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gartner Blogs Website</a></p>

<p>But shying away from the content for a moment, the process of getting such a conference to happen isn’t as trivial as it might seem. 
Where the preparations range from arranging a venue and finding a date that doesn’t clash too hard with all other conferences in the IT ecosystem, contacting and convincing interesting speakers to grace us with their presence, and setting up a marketing effort to get the word out there, the fun at this point has only begun. 
Facilities need to be arranged, such as making sure the proper recording material can be used to capture these talks for posterity. 
Catering and goodie bags need to be organized to give the attendees the best possible experience. 
You need to make sure that the people you invited to talk have the necessary arrangements to spend the night if needed and get transported for those who require transporting. 
A multitude of things can still get askew during the actual day, and firefighting mode is sometimes required at a moment’s notice.</p>

<p>All of this logistical work does not take away from the fact that we are proud of the ninth IT symphony we have put before our audience with the help of all of those willing to strip up their sleeves and help us out, not in the least the speakers and the technical staff of Elewijt Center that went well beyond the call of duty. 
And even though Beethoven’s magnum opus carried the same edition number, it is our wish that in contract with the maestro, we shall finish our tenth edition next year, and hope to see you all back again.</p>

<p>One closing Remark: The talks will be available on the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/OrdinaBelgiumJWorks" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">JOIN YouTube channel</a> as soon as they have left the capable hands of the post-production team.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Architecture" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="software architecture" /><category term="Cloud" /><category term="technical leadership" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We had JOIN, we had fun, we had seasons in the sun. It has already been a month since the 9th edition of the JOIN conference was concluded. And even though it had been ten years since the first edition, the skipped year due to the pandemic will cause us to have an additional anniversary edition next year. The aluminum edition will be a sight to see, and it would be a shame to miss it.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-10-24-ode-to-join/header.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-10-24-ode-to-join/header.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Waterfall vs Agile</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/agile/2022/10/19/waterfall-vs-agile.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Waterfall vs Agile" /><published>2022-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/agile/2022/10/19/waterfall-vs-agile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/agile/2022/10/19/waterfall-vs-agile.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Waterfall or agile for a new project? Benefits or disadvantages?</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#software-development-life-cycle">Software Development Life Cycle</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#waterfall">Waterfall</a></li>
      <li><a href="#agile">Agile</a></li>
      <li><a href="#scrumfallwaterscrumagilefallwatergile">Scrumfall/Waterscrum/Agilefall/Watergile</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>
<p>After my graduation until now, about 10 years, I have worked in many different teams and project, for various clients in various sectors.
During those years, many different styles of project management were used but they always came down to</p>
<ul>
  <li>the more traditional type of project management, also known as waterfall</li>
  <li>a more modern type known as agile</li>
  <li>something in between those 2</li>
</ul>

<p>It is widely known that agile is a big buzzword in more recent years, but what is it exactly?
What is the difference between agile and waterfall?
Which one can be used in which situation?
What are the benefits and disadvantages?</p>

<h1 id="software-development-life-cycle">Software Development Life Cycle</h1>
<p>It is important to know the purpose of a software development life cycle (SDLC). 
The usual explanation for this cycle is</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>A process that produces software with the highest quality and lowest cost in the shortest time possible. 
It typically provides a well-structured flow of phases that help an organization to quickly produce high-quality software 
which is well-tested and ready for production use.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A mouthful for saying that it provides guidance for delivering software as efficiently as possible, with high quality.</p>

<p>In a SDLC there is a focus on the following 6 phases:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Planning</li>
  <li>Analysis</li>
  <li>Design</li>
  <li>Implementation</li>
  <li>Testing &amp; Integration</li>
  <li>Maintenance</li>
</ul>

<p><img alt="SDLC order" src="/img/2022-10-19-waterfall-vs-agile/sdlc_order.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>There are multiple models of SDLC’s, but the most known are the <em>waterfall</em> and <em>agile</em> model.</p>

<h2 id="waterfall">Waterfall</h2>
<p>The waterfall model is the most traditional type of a SDLC. It has been around since 1970.
It divides the effort into a number of steps and defines that only one step can be active at the same time.
While it usually follows the 6 phases as described above, there’s no limit on it.</p>

<p>From where does it get its name?</p>

<p><img alt="Waterfall order" src="/img/2022-10-19-waterfall-vs-agile/waterfall_order.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>As you can see, it looks like a waterfall. Each step can only start after the previous one is done and thus it cascades down like a waterfall.</p>

<p>Now, when is a step done? Only when the specified artifacts that were defined at the beginning of the step are delivered and accepted.
For the implementation step, this can be a collection of software artifacts that satisfy the design.
For the testing step, it can be a test plan that demonstrates that all the requirements and design are working as intended.</p>

<p>A common mistake is that people think that you can not go back to a previous step. 
It is allowed, but it requires that you stop all work on the current step until the errors in the previous step have been resolved.</p>

<h3 id="pros">Pro’s</h3>
<ul>
  <li>It has detailed documentation and metrics</li>
  <li>The requirements are agreed upon and signed off</li>
  <li>There are less defects as there is rigorous planning and testing</li>
  <li>Defined start and end point which allows for easy measuring</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="cons">Con’s</h3>
<ul>
  <li>It starts slow as the requirements need to be defined in detail</li>
  <li>Changing those requirements takes a lot of effort</li>
  <li>The software is not visible until most of the development work is finished</li>
  <li>Less focus on the client because the requirements are the most important item</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="examples">Examples</h3>
<p>When do we use the waterfall model today?</p>
<ul>
  <li>When requirements can be reliably, quickly and thoroughly defined up front</li>
  <li>For very large teams where common understanding must be put in writing to avoid confusion and miscommunication</li>
  <li>When there is a defined budget and schedule given by the customer</li>
  <li>When there is not much involvement from the customer</li>
</ul>

<p>Building a bridge across a river is a good example of a project that is best done with a waterfall model.
That is a project where a clear schedule is needed and where the requirements need to be defined as soon as possible.
Saying “We will start with the first part of the bridge, evaluate that part and then decide if and how to continue with the remaining parts” is not a possibility here.</p>

<h2 id="agile">Agile</h2>
<p>The agile model has been created in direct response to the waterfall model.
It puts the focus on adaptive, simultaneous workflows which is the opposite from the linear flow of the waterfall model.</p>

<p>Instead of beginning with a complete knowledge of the requirements, the team develops a product in small cycles where small parts are build in a evolutionary way.
Each cycle contains the same steps as defined in the SDLC, but they can all be done at the same time, depending on the experience and skills of the team.
Contrary to the waterfall model, the customer can quickly see and evaluate how the project is advancing at the end of each cycle.
Needed changes to the requirements, based on this evaluation, can be done faster and implemented more easily.
This constant feedback from the client allows the team to adjust to the challenges as they arise and not when it is too late.</p>

<p><img alt="Agile order" src="/img/2022-10-19-waterfall-vs-agile/agile_order.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>The main idea behind the agile model is delivering business value early in the process to lower the risk associated with the development.</p>

<p>The most known implementations of the agile model are Scrum and Kanban, but they all share the same characteristics.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Simultaneous, incremental work</li>
  <li>Adaptability</li>
  <li>Faster and multiple deliverables</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="process">Process</h3>
<p>During agile development, the process usually looks like this:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Define a few initial requirements</li>
  <li>Design</li>
  <li>Develop</li>
  <li>Test</li>
  <li>Deploy</li>
  <li>Evaluate the result of the iteration</li>
  <li>Collect feedback from the various stakeholders</li>
  <li>Start the cycle again with new requirements and the feedback</li>
</ol>

<p><img alt="Agile cycle" src="/img/2022-10-19-waterfall-vs-agile/agile_cycle.jpg" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<h3 id="pros-1">Pro’s</h3>
<ul>
  <li>More project visibility at the end of each cycle</li>
  <li>It is a collaborative and practical approach for executing complex software development projects</li>
  <li>The client and stakeholders have frequent and early opportunities to evaluate the product</li>
  <li>Constant communication between team members so issues can be resolved proactively</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="cons-1">Con’s</h3>
<ul>
  <li>There is a risk for scope creep as agile projects generally have no set end date and thus additional features may be requested</li>
  <li>A multi-skilled resource pool is needed to deliver the project as all knowledge needs to be in the team</li>
  <li>Less detailed documentation as it is considered less important</li>
  <li>Fragmented output can be a problem as multiple teams may work on different components that then need to be put together</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="examples-1">Examples</h3>
<p>When do we use the agile model today?</p>
<ul>
  <li>If there are little to no requirements at the start of the project</li>
  <li>If your organization does not have strict processes to follow and the existing processes are lenient</li>
  <li>If the client or product owner can be highly available to follow the process</li>
  <li>When you’re trying to create something innovative that does not exist yet and needs to go to market quickly</li>
  <li>When the timeline is short and flexible</li>
  <li>When the budget has some wiggle room so that features can be prioritized</li>
</ul>

<p>Agile wins when the requirements are unclear from the beginning or still need to be discovered during the initial development.
More features will be produced in a shorter time frame and the team can be more flexible throughout the process.</p>

<p>A good example would be the development of a social media app. While the initial requirements are clear, further development depends heavily on the demands of the user.
So a start can be made with some basic features that can go quickly to market. Other features will then be implemented after the feedback of the business and most importantly the reactions of the users.</p>

<h2 id="scrumfallwaterscrumagilefallwatergile">Scrumfall/Waterscrum/Agilefall/Watergile</h2>
<p>This model might be known under even more names than the ones above. But it’s basically a software delivery lifecycle that tries to combine the best of both worlds in waterfall and agile.
It usually starts with an up-front design phase and ends with a legacy deployment mechanism, with agile development in between.</p>

<p><img alt="Scrumfall diagram" src="/img/2022-10-19-waterfall-vs-agile/scrumfall_diagram.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>But the name doesn’t matter. Everyone that knows a bit about agile knows that it’s a bad idea to do the entire design up-front and only then start developing. While that might work in a full waterfall model, it doesn’t in agile. 
Waterfall and agile are 2 fundamental different models with conflicts in interest as explained in the previous chapters.</p>

<h3 id="why">Why?</h3>
<p>So even though it’s not the best idea to mix these models, how does it happen that organizations use them?
The results may not be ideal, but it might be enough for some organizations. The agile model mentions all the time that there is not one solution that fits everyone. Every organization must find an approach that is effective for them and which enables them to deliver value.</p>

<p>Who doesn’t know an organization that follows Scrum to the letter, only to find out that it’s not the best approach for them?</p>

<p>Agile is for a large part about discovering new ways of working. As a result, the scrumfall model can be a temporary step towards a full agile transformation.
Now why would organizations keep using this hybrid form?</p>
<ul>
  <li>The IT department is agile and uses Scrum, but the other business departments have never been convinced. And so the organization is divided.</li>
  <li>The organization is stuck with an incomplete transformation and doesn’t know how to continue</li>
  <li>Or they’re in the middle of such a transformation and will finish it shortly</li>
  <li>The organization’s structure is made in such a way that deployment and operations cannot be done by the development teams</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="impact">Impact</h3>
<p>Now, how can this hybrid model impact your organization?
Let’s look at the following image:</p>

<p><img alt="Scrumfall time" src="/img/2022-10-19-waterfall-vs-agile/scrumfall_time.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>The first phase starts with the design as in every model. However, it’s waterfall design, so it takes a while to get everything designed in detail.
This means that during this phase, the development team has nothing to do. They’re just idle.
Once that phase is done and the developers can finally start working, they accelerate and can start delivering. But since the deployment process is still traditional waterfall, it takes a while to get it done. Which means that the feedback loop is going to be a lot slower than in modern agile models.</p>

<p>Slow feedback loops and long release cycles have a high negative impact on the value of the project as everything takes longer and results of various experimentations are harder to see.</p>

<h3 id="problems">Problems</h3>
<p>What are the major problems when you use this model?</p>
<ul>
  <li>Risk and waste: when using agile models, you get feedback by interacting with the business and the end-users. When designing up-front, you can’t anticipate changes in the demands. So when you’re not using a tight feedback loop, you might be creating the wrong thing. Which results in waste when you need to restart.</li>
  <li>Delayed feedback: since the development team is not doing the releases, it will take more time. Time that could be used to find out how the market responds to the new features.</li>
  <li>Long-term damage: the waste that is created has construction and maintenance costs, not to mention decrease in the team’s motivation. All these things have a long-term impact on the organization.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="way-out">Way out?</h3>
<p>The goal of any organization is to meet the goals of the corporate vision and mission. These goals should be achieved with the greatest efficiency and effect.
If that is done with waterfall or agile is less important. Even scrumfall might work for some organization, be it less effective than a “pure” model.</p>

<p>As with any model, experimentation must be done and improvements must be made. As in agile, this depends from organization to organization how it can be done. There is no one answer that fits for everyone.µ
The most important to keep in mind is that every organization needs to shift its approach to one that decreases waste while increasing quality and predictability.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Wouter&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Nivelle&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/wouter-nivelle/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;wouter-nivelle.jpg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Project Manager&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;wouter-nivelle-34a90b31&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;wouter.nivelle@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Wouter is a Project Manager at Ordina Belgium. Passionate about agile. Eager to share knowledge. Not afraid of challenges. Always interested in learning and discovering new things.&quot;}</name><email>wouter.nivelle@ordina.be</email></author><category term="Agile" /><category term="Agile" /><category term="Project Management" /><category term="Waterfall" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Waterfall or agile for a new project? Benefits or disadvantages?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-10-19-waterfall-vs-agile/header.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-10-19-waterfall-vs-agile/header.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">eXperience Agile 2022</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/conference/2022/10/03/experience-agile-2022.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="eXperience Agile 2022" /><published>2022-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/conference/2022/10/03/experience-agile-2022</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/conference/2022/10/03/experience-agile-2022.html"><![CDATA[<p>After 2 years of COVID, it was finally time for another conference. I’ve chosen the eXperience Agile conference in Lisbon, Portugal, from 26/09/2022 to 27/09/2022.
It was the 8th edition  of a global conference that focuses on gathering wisdom and best practices on business agility as well as technical agility.
Since I’m working with agile teams, I hoped to gather more knowledge and learn new things to apply to my teams.</p>

<p><img alt="Ready for the start" src="/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/ready_for_the_start.jpg" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>The first day contained 5 talks, agile safari’s, workshops and lightning talks.
The second day had the same format, but due to flight timings, I couldn’t see them all.</p>

<p>All talks were maximum thirty minutes, so the information was very concise.
In this blogpost, I’ll list some talks I found interesting.</p>

<h1 id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h1>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#fast-agile-by-ron-quartel">FAST Agile, by Ron Quartel</a></li>
  <li><a href="#optimise-your-neurophysiology-for-agile-thinking-by-delia-mccabe">Optimise your neurophysiology for agile thinking, by Delia McCabe</a></li>
  <li><a href="#practice-does-not-make-perfect-by-gil-broza">Practice does not make perfect, by Gil Broza</a></li>
  <li><a href="#understanding-value-streams-at-the-gemba-by-nigel-thurlow">Understanding value streams at the gemba, by Nigel Thurlow</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="fast-agile-by-ron-quartel">FAST Agile, by Ron Quartel</h1>

<p>The full title of the talk was ‘FAST Agile – The New (and Wild) Kid on the Agile Block’.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“Fluid Scaling Technology aka FAST Agile, is the outcome of an experiment in radical self-organization at scale. Not only did it work, but we also found it solved many of the issues that come with agile at scale that existing methods face. If you like Dave Snowden’s rewilding agile message, you are likely to see the promise in this radical new way of working built on Open Space Technology. Prepare to be surprised…”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img alt="FAST Agile" src="/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/fast_agile.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>During the talk, Ron referred a lot to the Cynefin model by <a href="https://thecynefin.co/about-us/about-cynefin-framework/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dave Snowden</a>. Explaining that model here would take me too far away from the purpose of this post.
In short, it helps to determine in what situation your company/project/team is (complex, complicated, chaos, obvious). And based on that situation, you can take calculated decisions.</p>

<p>Scrum can then be placed in the space between complicated and complex.
FAST sits in the complex space, next to the chaos border.</p>

<p><img alt="Scrum and FAST in Cynefin" src="/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/scrum_fast_cynefin.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>Now, what is FAST? It uses the principle of the Open Space Technology, where large groups of people come together, self-organise and set up a planning.
It stands for Fluid Scaling Technology. The A is just there so it sounds better.
How the process works:</p>
<ol>
  <li>It merges teams into a tribe</li>
  <li>Everyone throws their work on a wall</li>
  <li>Everyone self-organizes around the work</li>
  <li>2 days later, everyone meets back and shares their progress</li>
  <li>Repeat from the start</li>
</ol>

<p>It’s an agile method where scaling is built-in. Certain conditions must be met, but that’s also true for Scrum and agile in general.</p>

<p>How does FAST help?</p>
<ul>
  <li>It’s a pure complex system, unlike other scaling methods like SAFe which are complicated in nature. The Cynefin model teaches us that complicated systems must be solved with complicated models, and complex with complex.</li>
  <li>It has been designed to not transform to zombie agile</li>
  <li>It focuses on both Discovery and Delivery while other agile methods focus on Delivery</li>
</ul>

<p>More information on FAST can be found at <a href="https://fluid.scaling.tech/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fluid Scaling Tech</a>.</p>

<h1 id="optimise-your-neurophysiology-for-agile-thinking-by-delia-mccabe">Optimise your neurophysiology for agile thinking, by Delia McCabe</h1>

<p>A surprising talk about the functioning of the brain and how it correlates with agile.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“Thinking occurs across a sensitive and sophisticated neural network. Our neurophysiology depends heavily on lifestyle choices, which include the nutrients we consume. Other lifestyle factors, which include sleep quality, physical activity, and work and relationships, also impact this sophisticated network, although nutrition  forms the foundation of our neurophysiology. It is therefore the first principle we need to address if we aim to maximise cognitive strategies such as agile, creative, and flexible thinking.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img alt="Feed your brain" src="/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/feed_your_brain.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>I was most curious about this talk, as it doesn’t immediately connect with an agile conference. She said it herself that she was surprised to have been invited, but took it as a challenge to explain how the brain works and how that affects the agile way of thinking.</p>

<p>She started the talk with explaining how our brains have evolved to work in a jungle environment, to survive.
But that the current office life is a lot different and our brains have difficulties handling it. Back in the ancient times, stress was present in short bursts (for example when hunting), but not continuously like it is in the current times.</p>

<p>She explained how the brain needs to be nourished correctly in order to be able to receive new information.
If the brain is not nourished properly, it will not be able to create new neural links and thus not process new experiences.
So for example, when you’re explaining something new to another person, if that person’s brain is not nourished as it should be, that person will not process the information correctly, if at all.</p>

<p>More information on this subject can be found at <a href="https://www.lighterbrighteryou.life/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</p>

<h1 id="practice-does-not-make-perfect-by-gil-broza">Practice does not make perfect, by Gil Broza</h1>

<p>Almost every company uses agile nowadays. But not everyone gets it right.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“These days, almost every organization is on an Agile journey. And yet, most companies have trouble achieving real agility. Why is that? Aren’t the ingredients for effective transformations available to everyone? There is no shortage of motivation, established practices, detailed processes, ever-improving tools, literature, consultants, employees with agile experience, and certifications. Gil Broza, author of “The Agile Mindset” and “The Human Side of Agile”, thinks that one particular ingredient has been overlooked in the mad rush to adopt Agile. In this session, he leads us on an exploration of that ingredient and its crucial role in successful Agile journeys.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img alt="Practice does not make perfect" src="/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/practice_does_not_make_perfect.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>The talk started with the explanation of the logical levels model.
It goes top-down from identity and role, to values and belief, to capability, behaviour and environment.
He gave the following example in his current role:</p>

<p><img alt="Logical levels example" src="/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/logical_levels.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>He continued explaining the starting point of many agile journeys.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Traditional values</th>
      <th>Traditional beliefs</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Get it right the first time</td>
      <td>Customers know what they want</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Minimize cost and time</td>
      <td>Putting a plan together is worth it</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Make early commitments</td>
      <td>Okay to have multiple constraints</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Follow industry standards</td>
      <td>People are resources</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The above is of course not very agile. But it’s a starting point where many organisations started.
He then went on explaining how the above works in the logical levels model and how to adapt it.</p>

<p>But either way, as he stated, “Practices don’t matter, mind-set does”.
A good example is the table below, where you can see that just giving things a different name does not work if the traditional belief stays.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Practice/role/artifact</th>
      <th>Was conceived as</th>
      <th>A traditional mindset sees it as</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Daily standup</td>
      <td>Regular check-in to maximize the team’s value output</td>
      <td>Daily status for maximizing work-the-plan</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Product backlog</td>
      <td>Prioritized list of valuable deliverables the team might do</td>
      <td>Project plan</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Pair programming</td>
      <td>Collaboration to minimize the risk of employing humans</td>
      <td>Under-utilization</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Scrum Master</td>
      <td>Servant leader, helping the team succeed as a team</td>
      <td>Project manager, ensures process compliance</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Sprint demo</td>
      <td>Feedback, for adaptation</td>
      <td>Frequent deadline for sign-off, tracking and accountability</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>More information of his talk can be found <a href="https://3pvantage.com/resources/Gil%20Broza%20-%20Practice%20Does%20not%20Make%20Perfect.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>.</p>

<h1 id="understanding-value-streams-at-the-gemba-by-nigel-thurlow">Understanding value streams at the gemba, by Nigel Thurlow</h1>

<p>The full title of this talk was “Understanding value streams at the gemba, not from the office”.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“He’ll cover what Lean metrics really are, how scaling should work, take you into queuing theory, and then back to the Genba where the real improvements happen. Learn what a real value stream is and how to uncover the real costs of doing business. This and a whole lot more of mind bending topics.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img alt="Value stream mapping" src="/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/value_stream_mapping.png" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>Now this was a talk that was filled with information. There were 71 (!) slides that had to be told in 30 minutes. That is a lot of information to transfer in a short period of time.
However, Nigel managed to do so quite well.
I’m not going to pretend I understood everything, but it was interesting nonetheless.</p>

<p>He talked about the Flow system, about complex versus complicated environments, about various tools and how they’re only visualisations, etc… .
There was way too much to tell here in this blog post, but I’ll try to share some things I’m going to keep in mind.</p>

<p>Value is cross organisation. You can try to sub-optimize in the IT department, but if you don’t take the other departments with you, the value generated will not be optimal.
The value stream contains all the people, machines, technology and skills needed to complete the end to end product delivery.</p>

<p>Closely tying in to the above is the genba/gemba and real value stream.
He explains that growth, costs, time-to-market and staff attrition are not problems, but outcomes. And that if you want to change those outcomes, you’ll have to change how you do work.
This is where genba comes into play. It’s Japanese for “actual place”.</p>

<p><img alt="Gemba" src="/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/gemba.jpg" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 750px;" /></p>

<p>It means you need to go the place in your company where the actual value is created. Nigel explained how he helped to transform a corn factory by actually doing an 8-hour shift on the factory floor.
This gave him better insights in one shift than his previous 3 weeks of observation. This enabled him to make changes to the production line and added value to the company.</p>

<p>More information can be found on <a href="https://nigelthurlow.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">his website</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Wouter&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Nivelle&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/wouter-nivelle/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;wouter-nivelle.jpg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Project Manager&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;wouter-nivelle-34a90b31&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;wouter.nivelle@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Wouter is a Project Manager at Ordina Belgium. Passionate about agile. Eager to share knowledge. Not afraid of challenges. Always interested in learning and discovering new things.&quot;}</name><email>wouter.nivelle@ordina.be</email></author><category term="Conference" /><category term="Agile" /><category term="Conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After 2 years of COVID, it was finally time for another conference. I’ve chosen the eXperience Agile conference in Lisbon, Portugal, from 26/09/2022 to 27/09/2022. It was the 8th edition of a global conference that focuses on gathering wisdom and best practices on business agility as well as technical agility. Since I’m working with agile teams, I hoped to gather more knowledge and learn new things to apply to my teams.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/ExperienceAgile2022.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-10-03-experience-agile-2022/ExperienceAgile2022.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Snitching On Your Colleagues Using Cloud Magic</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/internship/2022/07/07/snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Snitching On Your Colleagues Using Cloud Magic" /><published>2022-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/internship/2022/07/07/snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/internship/2022/07/07/snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="table-of-contents">Table Of Contents</h1>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></p>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#the-task-at-hand">The Task At Hand</a></li>
  <li><a href="#exploring-the-environment">Exploring The Environment</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#azure-repos">Azure Repos</a></li>
      <li><a href="#pipeline">Pipeline</a></li>
      <li><a href="#library">Library</a></li>
      <li><a href="#service-connections">Service Connections</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#into-the-rabbit-hole-setting-up-the-pipeline">Into The Rabbit-Hole : Setting Up The Pipeline</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#before-we-dive-in">Before We Dive In</a></li>
      <li><a href="#basic-tasks">Basic Tasks</a></li>
      <li><a href="#containerization">Containerization</a></li>
      <li><a href="#setting-up-a-cloud-database">Setting Up A Cloud Database</a></li>
      <li><a href="#provisioning-a-cloud-cluster">Provisioning A Cloud Cluster</a></li>
      <li><a href="#giving-a-signal">Giving A Signal</a></li>
      <li><a href="#a-visual-representation">A Visual Representation</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#out-of-the-frying-pan-and-into-the-fire-creating-our-own-task">Out Of The Frying Pan And Into The Fire: Creating Our Own Task</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#requirements">Requirements</a></li>
      <li><a href="#getting-the-logs">Getting The Logs</a></li>
      <li><a href="#filtering-and-saving-failures">Filtering And Saving Failures</a></li>
      <li><a href="#factory-fresh">Factory Fresh</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#the-berry-on-top--our-physical-feedback">The Berry On Top: Our Physical Feedback</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#dollar-store-google-assistant">Dollar Store Google Assistant</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#the-good-the-bad---the-ugly--summary">The Good, The Bad &amp; … The Ugly?</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>

<p>7 weeks ago I started my internship at Ordina Mechelen.
I had several project options available all looking to touch new and unknown tech that might be relevant for future operations.</p>

<p>My inner Judas spoke to me when I saw a listing about a project that would shoot toy rockets at developers if they broke a build, and it would provide a great opportunity to pull myself out of my comfort zone focusing more on Devops and Cloud platforms rather than pure programming.
Sadly due to a global hardware shortage the toy rocket launcher was not available for delivery anymore, so I decided to use a raspberry pi to fetch the build logs and convert them into audio using google text to speech.</p>

<h1 id="the-task-at-hand">The Task At Hand</h1>

<p>The project described a ci-cd pipeline that would trigger a raspberry pi once a build fails, then in response the pi would operate a toy rocket launcher unit that would target the developer responsible for breaking the build.
As such the final project can be broken down into these steps:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Create a sacrificial bare-bones spring boot project to put through the ringer</li>
  <li>Create a pipeline which performs some cookie cutter tasks</li>
  <li>Expand pipeline to setup AWS infrastructure</li>
  <li>Expand pipeline to provision said infrastructure</li>
  <li>Create a custom pipeline task to fetch and push build logs</li>
  <li>Configure raspberry pi to host a node.js server</li>
  <li>Listen for new log files</li>
  <li>If new log files have been found, search for error messages and convert those via text to speech(TTS)</li>
  <li>Broadcast the failures of your colleagues</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="exploring-the-environment">Exploring The Environment</h1>
<p>I’m going to dive right into the meat and potatoes of this project and write about the pipeline since the spring boot application does nothing more than display some basic html and runs a couple of unit tests.
The devops environment that was used consisted of a couple of things.</p>
<h3 id="azure-repos">Azure Repos</h3>
<p>A simple git instance on the Azure platform used for version control of our spring boot project.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/repo_position.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 100%;" /></p>

<h3 id="pipeline">Pipeline</h3>
<p>The bread and butter of our operation. Using a data serialization language called yaml we are able to define each individual task we want applied to our code.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/pipeline_position.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 100%;" /></p>

<h3 id="library">Library</h3>
<p>A place to store key value pairs that we can group and later reference in our yaml file.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/library_position.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 100%;" /></p>

<h3 id="service-connections">Service Connections</h3>
<p>Predefined connections to internal (Azure) or external services from which we can later extract credentials to gain access in the pipeline.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/service_connection_position.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 100%;" /></p>

<h1 id="into-the-rabbit-hole-setting-up-the-pipeline">Into The Rabbit-Hole: Setting Up The Pipeline</h1>
<p>In this section I will initially explain how to set up some basic tasks within our yaml file for building and testing. 
Next, I’ll move on to containerizing our build. 
Finally, I’ll explain how I have used IaC (Infrastructure as Code) to firstly spin up an RDS (AWS) instance based on Postgres and secondly use Helm to deploy the application to an EKS (AWS) cluster owned by JWorks.</p>
<h3 id="before-we-dive-in">Before We Dive In</h3>
<p>Before we dive in, there are some nice to know things about the inner workings and structure of a pipeline defined in a yaml file.
I’ll briefly go over some key definitions, so you can follow along when each individual task gets explained.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Triggers :
    <ul>
      <li>Triggers are (like the word implies) what starts a pipeline</li>
      <li>These can be changes in a branch like <strong><em>main</em></strong> or <strong><em>develop</em></strong> but could also be specific events happening in another pipeline such as failed jobs/stages or a specific variable value</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Variables :
    <ul>
      <li>A hardcoded variable defined at the start of your pipeline</li>
      <li>A variable group containing secret values like tokens that can not be acquired using service connections</li>
      <li>Both of these options can be defined at the same time or individually and used anywhere in the pipeline including in additional task commands if the task allows it.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Stages :
    <ul>
      <li>Defines what steps your pipeline should take in what order.</li>
      <li>Encapsulation of <strong><em>stage</em></strong> sections</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Stage :
    <ul>
      <li>A section of your pipeline</li>
      <li>Can be given a name of your choosing eg: Test,Docker,CloudSetup …</li>
      <li>Encapsulation for <strong><em>jobs</em></strong></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Jobs :
    <ul>
      <li>Encapsulation of <strong><em>job</em></strong> sections</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Job :
    <ul>
      <li>Can be given a name of your choosing just like the <strong><em>stage</em></strong> section</li>
      <li>Can be given a <strong><em>pool</em></strong> attribute to define which agent OS has to run this job</li>
      <li>Encapsulation of one or more <strong><em>task</em></strong> sections</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Task :
    <ul>
      <li>A pre-built or custom-made task to be performed on your pipeline run.</li>
      <li>Has a variety of attributes that can be manually filled up such as credentials or dictating your preferred working directories</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Agents :
    <ul>
      <li>A machine hosted by the cloud provider (Azure in our case) that runs on a specific OS</li>
      <li>Defined in the <strong><em>pool</em></strong> attribute of a <strong><em>job</em></strong> or at the start of a pipeline.</li>
      <li>Mostly a clean slate with only some essential software pre-installed eg: Docker</li>
      <li>Gets wiped after use in order to accommodate the next job.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>All of the above gets combined into a structure that resembles following code.</p>

<div class="language-yaml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="na">variables</span><span class="pi">:</span>
<span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">group</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">my-variable-group</span>

<span class="na">trigger</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">main</span>

<span class="na">pool</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="na">vmImage</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">ubuntu-latest</span>

<span class="na">stages</span><span class="pi">:</span>
<span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">stage</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="na">jobs</span><span class="pi">:</span>
  <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">job</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">myJob</span>
    <span class="na">steps</span><span class="pi">:</span>
    <span class="pi">-</span> <span class="na">script</span><span class="pi">:</span> <span class="s">echo "Hello"</span> 
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="basic-tasks">Basic Tasks</h3>
<p>Following are the pipeline tasks used to test our java project, generate a test rapport and then build it using Maven.</p>
<h4 id="maven-test">Maven Test</h4>
<p>To test our application we will be using JUnit because of the pre-existing support given by Azure. 
This will also generate a test rapport during each pipeline run based on the unit tests defined in our project.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/maven_test.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<h4 id="maven-build">Maven Build</h4>
<p>A standard task using the Maven goal of ‘package’ which returns a JAR file that can later be used by Docker.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/maven_build.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<h4 id="copying-and-creating-an-artifact">Copying And Creating An Artifact</h4>
<p>In order to use our build across multiple agents we need to create an artifact out of the build.
This artifact gets stored within the pipeline and can get called upon whenever we please.
We do this by first copying our build to a directory on our agent that functions as the default staging directory for artifacts.
By using a second task we take that build and publish it to our pipeline storage.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/copy_and_publish.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<h3 id="containerization">Containerization</h3>
<p>Here we use the artifact we created during our last job to create an image and push it to Dockerhub.</p>
<h4 id="fetching-our-artifact">Fetching Our Artifact</h4>
<p>First we have to fetch the artifact that we uploaded to our pipeline and place it in the appropriate directory on our new agent.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/download_artifact.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<h4 id="creating-an-image">Creating An Image</h4>
<p>Then we use said artifact together with a Dockerfile that was previously placed within our java project to create and upload an image to Dockerhub.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/docker_task.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<h3 id="setting-up-a-cloud-database">Setting Up A Cloud Database</h3>
<p>In this job we will use Terraform to set up an RDS (AWS) database based on Postgres for our containerized java application.
Our Terraform files are stored in the java project under a folder called infrastructure and can be called upon directly, alternatively a remote folder containing Terraform files can be specified if you want or need to split up your project files.
Credentials needed to get access to AWS services come from a manually pre-defined service connection.</p>
<h4 id="installing-terraform">Installing Terraform</h4>
<p>In order to use Terraform on our agent we have to first install it to our agent since it is not supplied by default.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/terraform_install_task.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<h4 id="initializing-terraform">Initializing Terraform</h4>
<p>This task performs several initialization steps in order to prepare the current working directory for use with Terraform.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/terraform_init.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 75%;" /></p>

<h4 id="terraform-plan">Terraform Plan</h4>
<p>Plans out what configurations and steps will be made once the apply command is given.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/terraform_plan_task.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 75%;" /></p>

<h4 id="terraform-apply">Terraform Apply</h4>
<p>Excecuting our Terraform plan defined in the previous step.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/terraform_apply.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 75%;" /></p>

<h3 id="provisioning-a-cloud-cluster">Provisioning A Cloud Cluster</h3>
<p>Now that we have an image of our app and place to store data to only one crucial step remains, launching our application.
Our application gets deployed to EKS (Elastic Kubernetes Service) which is another AWS service designed for running cloud based Kubernetes.
In order to do so a Helm chart has been made which like the Terraform files is stored under the infrastructure directory of our project.
These charts are defined in a yaml format where specifications for Kubernetes are being made eg: Name of the app, Kind , Amount of replicas, Image to use …</p>

<h4 id="helm-deploy">Helm Deploy</h4>
<p>Using our Helm chart and a service connection allowing us to deploy to the Jworks cluster, we deploy our application, which gets pulled from Dockerhub, to the “stage-thomas-more” namespace within EKS.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/helm_task.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 75%;" /></p>

<h3 id="giving-a-signal">Giving A Signal</h3>
<p>Now that everything has been set up and all the services are up and running it’s time to give our developers a heads-up.
I did this using a Telegram bot that will broadcast a message for every build that has run.
The bot token was stored in the <strong>library</strong> as a secret key-value pair.</p>
<h4 id="creating-our-bot">Creating Our Bot</h4>
<p>This is a prerequisite if you want to work with Telegram since a bot token and a chat id are required to function.
Telegram has a neat tutorial on how to create your own bot using the “Botfather” which you can find here : <a href="https://core.telegram.org/bots" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Botfather</a></p>
<h4 id="sending-out-notifications">Sending Out Notifications</h4>
<p>Now that we have our bot token and a chat id we can define a message that gets sent everytime the task is reached.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/telegram_task.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<h3 id="a-visual-representation">A Visual Representation</h3>
<p>Displayed below you will find two images representing the pipeline and the goals they accomplish on the Cloud.</p>

<p>For now pay no attention to the little logo displaying Eric Cartman, this is the image I used to represent my custom task which we will get to in the following section.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/pipeline_flow.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 75%;" /></p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/AWS_diagram_final_image.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 75%;" /></p>

<h1 id="out-of-the-frying-pan-and-into-the-fire-creating-our-own-task">Out Of The Frying Pan And Into The Fire: Creating Our Own Task</h1>
<p>During week 5 all of the above was learned, implemented and configured to a working state so a question was asked by Frederick Bousson the solutions lead at the Jworks Ordina Unit if it was possible to create a custom task for use in the pipeline.</p>

<p>Up for another challenge I stepped into the pretty unexplored (And not fully documented) lands of developing a task for a pipeline.
The main objective of the task is to get the pipeline logs from a predefined pipeline run or from the current one as default.
Those logs get filtered and send to a DynamoDB instance hosted on AWS.</p>

<h4 id="requirements">Requirements</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Node.js</li>
  <li>TFX : A packaging tool</li>
  <li>Microsoft VSS Web Extension SDK package</li>
  <li>Some experience writing in Javascript or Typescript</li>
  <li>A Visual Studio publisher account (free)</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="getting-the-logs">Getting The Logs</h4>
<p>This was done using the Azure Devops REST API: <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/rest/api/azure/devops/?view=azure-devops-rest-7.1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Documentation</a></p>

<p>To get builds, a couple of things are required:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The Azure Devops organization name</li>
  <li>The project name</li>
  <li>The build number</li>
  <li>Authorization</li>
</ul>

<p>While the values for point one and two were pretty straightforward gaining access to the <strong>build logs</strong> required a <strong>build id</strong> instead of a <strong>build number</strong> , and since the <strong>build id</strong> can not be traced through the UI of Azure Devops some nested API requests were required.</p>

<p>The Authorization was gained through the creation of a PAT token that can be used as a header in the GET Request.</p>
<h4 id="filtering-and-saving-failures">Filtering And Saving Failures</h4>
<p>Now that we have our desired logs all that remains is filtering, formatting and sending those logs to DynamoDB.
In order to complete this operation the following steps were taken:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Set up authorization in a way that allows developers to use their AWS service connection.</li>
  <li>Use the AWS SDK combined with the credentials from the service connection to authorize the user.</li>
  <li>Filter the received logs which had a format of plain text using regex to find possible error messages</li>
  <li>Format the error messages together with the developer responsible for the build and the time of build.</li>
  <li>Push our formatted object to DynamoDB</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="factory-fresh">Factory Fresh</h4>
<p>Eh Voilà!
Our extension does everything we hoped it would do, so it’s time implement it in our pipeline.</p>

<p>First we compile our Typescript to Javascript since the index.js file is the default node entry point.
We then package our extension, and finally upload it using the management portal where we share it with our organizations of choice.</p>

<p>The result:</p>

<p>In my publisher account:
<img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/custom_task_in_marketplace.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 75%;" /></p>

<p>In the pipeline:
<img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/custom_extension_task.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<p>Want to check out the code? Take a look at the project repo : <a href="https://github.com/MarienL1995/customTaskPublic" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Github</a></p>

<h1 id="the-berry-on-top--our-physical-feedback">The Berry On Top : Our Physical Feedback</h1>
<p>Almost there!
Finally, it is time for the actual dirty work namely snitching on our dear colleagues.
To do this I only needed two things, a raspberry pi and a bluetooth speaker.</p>

<h3 id="dollar-store-google-assistant">Dollar Store Google Assistant</h3>
<p>Initially we had planned to use a toy rocket launcher as our physical feedback machine.
That idea was scrapped however because of a global shortage (or tremendous price increase) for all hardware components.</p>

<p>Next the Google Assistant came to mind which is embedded in Android devices or a Google home speaker.
The problem with this idea unfortunately was that the Google Assistant was never designed to take in text input through an API because devices running Google Assistant had no direct endpoints.
Now we could in fact work around this and set up a Home automation system like Home Assistant or Node Red but this would mean that our speaker could never change location without reconfiguring access to its new network.</p>

<p>A final solution I came up with in secret while my mentor was away on a conference in Valencia, was to run a Node.js server on a Raspberry Pi that after booting takes a reference log from our DynamoDB database.
Every minute it would get the latest log available and compare it to the log it had stored, this way when a difference in logs had been found it knew it was time to call out the developer.</p>

<p>Through a nifty npm package we are able to send our text message that we want converted to an audio file and get an url in return pointing to an audio file.
Using Node file system I programmatically created a text file where each audio url alternated with a path to a local audio file gets written on a line in the previously created text file.
What I had just created was a playlist which dictated the order of audio files to be played.
All I had to do now was hook it up to a media player.</p>

<p><strong><em>note</em></strong>: This not the ideal solution, but it allowed the Pi and speaker to be portable to any location as long as we could connect it to wi-fi.</p>

<p>A succesfull pipeline run broadcast(Sound up):</p>

<div class="responsive-video">
  
    <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W4LZsEbTRF4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"> </iframe>
  
</div>

<p>A failed pipeline run broadcast(Sound up):</p>

<div class="responsive-video">
  
    <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6PS0K2zdW-o" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="true"> </iframe>
  
</div>

<h1 id="the-good-the-bad---the-ugly--summary">The Good, The Bad &amp; … The Ugly? : Summary</h1>

<p>Like I mentioned at the start of this blog, there were a number of different project options to choose from as an internship topic.
The reason I went with the ci-cd route is that I knew it would pull me out of my comfort zone and broaden my view on development in general.</p>

<p>While having touched on basic CLI environments like Docker or Bash it always felt cryptic to use a multitude of flags and if you messed up the error messages weren’t all that clear compared to an error with a web framework like React for example.</p>

<p>After 7 weeks of submerging myself mostly in configuration files like .yaml and .tf(Terraform) combined with CLI tools such as kubectl for Kubernetes, psql for Postgres and AWS CLI for AWS Configuration, I’m glad to say that i feel a lot more at home touching on tools not necessarily meant for pure programming.</p>

<p>For a total recap of tools and software used during the project, I put together the following image.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/tech_summary.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 75%;" /></p>

<p>As a final sendoff I want to say a quick thank you to my mentor Nick Geudens for guiding me through the jungle of DevOps and AWS and to Frederick Bousson for coming up with the project and allowing me the opportunity to execute it.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Lander&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Marien&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/lander_marien/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;lander_marien.jpg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Intern&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;lander-mariën&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;lander.marien@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Lander is a graduating student Programming at Thomas More Campus De Nayer.&quot;}</name><email>lander.marien@ordina.be</email></author><category term="Internship" /><category term="Spring" /><category term="Spring Boot" /><category term="Git" /><category term="DevOps" /><category term="Docker" /><category term="Kubernetes" /><category term="Terraform" /><category term="Helm" /><category term="Azure" /><category term="Internet Of Things" /><category term="RaspberryPi" /><category term="Javascript" /><category term="Node.js" /><category term="AWS" /><category term="DynamoDB" /><category term="RDS" /><category term="Postgres" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Table Of Contents]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/Betrayal.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-07-07-snitching-on-your-colleagues-using-cloud-magic/Betrayal.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Clean Agile - Back to Basics</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/leadership/2022/06/30/clean-agile.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Clean Agile - Back to Basics" /><published>2022-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/leadership/2022/06/30/clean-agile</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/leadership/2022/06/30/clean-agile.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-reasons-for-agile">The Reasons for Agile</a></li>
  <li><a href="#business-practices">Business Practices</a></li>
  <li><a href="#team-practices">Team Practices</a></li>
  <li><a href="#technical-practices">Technical Practices</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>

<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>

<p>Coming from a non-programming background, I was always interested to hear or learn about Agile methodology but with a fear that Agile vocabulary would be too techy for me. This book helped me to get rid out of my fears once and for all. In addition, having been in a High Performance Team using Agile Methodologies at Ordina for 5 years, “Uncle Bob”(Robert C. Martin) helped me via his <em>Back to Basics</em> book to restructure what I experienced and helped me to create my own lessons learned.</p>

<p>This book is for programmers and non-programmers alike. It aims not to go into technical details but focusses more on explaining what the fundamentals of Agile are.</p>

<p>Agile’s ideology and values emerge from a group of 17 programming experts during the fall of 2000 who were willing to create an alternative of what is called the Scientific Management (which inspired the idea of “Waterfall” development).</p>

<p>Four basic values came out of this gathering and are the central idea of the Agile Manifesto that emerged from that moment:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Individuals and interactions</strong> over processed and tools</li>
  <li><strong>Working software</strong> over comprehensive documentation</li>
  <li><strong>Customer collaboration</strong> over contract negotiation</li>
  <li><strong>Responding to change</strong> over following a plan</li>
</ul>

<p>Uncle Bob then gives as an introduction an Agile overview.
 He does this by responding to the question: <strong>“how do you manage a software project”</strong>.
 Therefore, he uses the metaphor of the Iron Cross, a management trade-off that needs to be done in all projects. One has to pick three out of the four goals: Good, Fast, Cheap, Done , in order to manage a project. Reaching all of these in the project is not possible.</p>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-06-30-clean-agile/clean-agile-1.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 100%;" /></p>

<p>In this context, he warns that Agile is not the Holy Grail, but only a framework that helps managers and developers to execute the goals they decide to take on <em>by providing real data</em>. This data is needed to make good decisions. Without data, no project can be well managed.</p>

<p>This way he introduces some Agile tools (known from everyone that already worked with one of the Agile methodologies): burn-down charts, story points, business value, iterations. These have only one goal: every stakeholder of the project has a constant feedback on how it evolutes. These are thus created not to control the team but to make appropriate adjustments to correctly manage the project.</p>

<h1 id="the-reasons-for-agile">The Reasons for Agile</h1>

<p>If you have to read only one chapter of this book, it should be this one. In it, Uncle Bob reminds us that even if many of the Agile tools have been proliferating since 20 years (Scrum, Kanban, XP, SAFe, etc.), it makes no sense to use them without keeping in mind the essence of Agility.</p>

<p>There are the two straightforward reasons of using Agile methodologies: <strong>professionalism</strong> and <strong>reasonable expectations</strong> of our customer.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Professionalism in the sense that developers are those who design today’s world (software is everywhere). And as the quote of the first Spiderman movie warns: <strong>“With great power comes great responsibility”</strong>.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-06-30-clean-agile/clean-agile-2.jpg" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<ul>
  <li>Customers have the right to have Reasonable expectations :
    <ul>
      <li>Continuous technical readiness: in order to counter artificial delays, the system should be technically deployable at the end of each iteration (Clean Code, Automated Testing)</li>
      <li>Stable productivity and inexpensive adaptability: customers and managers don’t expect the project to slow down with time (Continuous Refactoring, Architecture Design, Clean Code)</li>
      <li>Continuous improvement: early problems must fade away and the system should get better and better with time (Pair Programming, TDD, Refactoring, Simple Design)</li>
      <li>Fearless competence: developers do not have to fear touching an ugly code (Clean Code)</li>
      <li>QA should find nothing and Test Automation: If QA finds a problem, development team should figure out what went wrong in the process so that QA finds nothing next time (TDD, Continuous Integration, Acceptance Testing)</li>
      <li>We cover for each other: it is your responsibility to make sure that at least one other team member can cover for you (Pair Programming, Whole Team, Collective Ownership)</li>
      <li>Honest estimates: developers need to provide estimates based on what they do and don’t know (Planning Game, Whole Team)</li>
      <li>You need to say “no”: no matter which pressure is on you, you have to say “no” if the answer is really no (Whole Team)</li>
      <li>Mentoring and continuous aggressive learning: as the industry changes quickly, you should follow this flow and learn to teach (Whole Team)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>In this state of mind, he concludes this chapter with the XP Customer and Developer Bill of Rights:</p>

<p><strong>Customer Bill of Rights</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>You have the right to an overall plan, to know what can be accomplished when and at what cost.</li>
  <li>You have the right to get the most possible value out of every programming week.</li>
  <li>You have the right to see progress in a running system, proven to work by passing repeatable tests that you specify.</li>
  <li>You have the right to change your mind, to substitute functionality, and to change priorities without paying exorbitant costs.</li>
  <li>You have the right to be informed of schedule changes, in time to choose how to reduce the scope to restore the original date. You can cancel at any time and be left with a useful working system reflecting investment to date.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Developer Bill of Rights</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>You have the right to know what is needed, with clear declarations of priority.</li>
  <li>You have the right to produce quality work at all times.</li>
  <li>You have the right to ask for and receive help from peers, managers, and customers.</li>
  <li>You have the right to make and update your own estimates.</li>
  <li>You have the right to accept your responsibilities instead of having them assigned to you.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-06-30-clean-agile/clean-agile-3.jpg" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 100%;" /></p>

<p>Based on those fundamental reasons, the next 3 chapters aim to explain the practices of XP (Business, Team and Technical wise) - keeping in mind that Agile is the foundation of an <strong>ethical</strong> standard of software. Nothing else.</p>

<h1 id="business-practices">Business Practices</h1>

<p>As Uncle Bob reminds, XP Business-facing-practices are including the concepts of Planning, Small Releases, Acceptance Tests and Whole Team.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Planning</strong> and day-to-day management are handled through story points. The concept behind SP is that those points are not estimated time, but estimated effort. The aim for using story points is to give a day-to-day estimation of the workload. Each iteration will help the next iteration to estimate more precisely what still needs to be developed. But, as he highlights: “that estimate is not a promise, and the team has not failed if the velocity is lower. The aim is thus only to produce data necessary to manage the project correctly</li>
  <li><strong>Small releases</strong> practices are handled through the concept of <em>Continuous Delivery</em>. He mentions that nowadays, the best Source Code Control used is Git thanks to some of its characteristics (no checkout time, no conflicts of committing, tiny decoupled modules, rapid commit frequency, fast-running test suite…)</li>
  <li><strong>Acceptance Tests</strong> practices are handled through the concept of <em>Behavior-Driven Development</em> (BDD): The business writes formal tests (Given…, When…, Then…) describing the behavior of each story, and Developers automate those tests, which become the <em>Definition of Done</em></li>
  <li><strong>Whole Team</strong> practice has been conceptualized to cancel the mental separation between the customer and the developers. “A development team is composed of many roles including managers, testers, technical writers, etc.”</li>
</ul>

<p>Business practices have thus one aim: to increase and facilitate communication between business and developers. <strong>“That communication breeds trust”</strong>.</p>

<h1 id="team-practices">Team Practices</h1>

<p>Team practices are aimed at governing the relationship between all team members for the sake of the project they work on. These are composed by: Metaphor, Sustainable Pace, Collective Ownership and Continuous Integration.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Metaphor</strong> practice is the fact that a model (with its own vocabulary) is created to explain the problem domain in order to get <strong>everyone</strong> agreed on it (developers as well as management or customers or..)</li>
  <li><strong>Sustainable Pace</strong> practices remind to keep workload at a life equilibrium, through diminishing as much a possible overtime or “marathons”, and keeping in mind that “sleep is the most precious ingredient in the life of a programmer”</li>
  <li><strong>Collective ownership</strong> practices defines the fact that even if sometimes a developer needs to specialize in a particular domain, he should also generalize, obligating himself to work on other areas of the code, less known for him</li>
  <li><strong>Continuous Integration</strong> practices is the fact that the continuous build should never break</li>
</ul>

<p>For Uncle Bob, these practices “help small teams to behave like true teams”.</p>

<h1 id="technical-practices">Technical Practices</h1>

<p>While these practices are less used by programmers, Uncle Bob pinpoints that they are the very core of Agile and not using them is creating an “ineffective flaccid shell of what it was intended to be”.
 These practices are the following: Test-Driven Development (TDD), Refactoring, Simple Design and Pair Programming.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>TDD</strong> practice are for developers what double-entry bookkeeping is for accountants. Uncle Bob reminds the <a href="http://butunclebob.com/ArticleS.UncleBob.TheThreeRulesOfTdd" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">three rules of TDD</a> but, more important, he explains by an example of how courageous it is to keep the code clean and orderly. Thanks to that, we can act like professionals.</li>
  <li><strong>Refactoring</strong> is the “practice of improving the structure of the code without altering the behavior, as defined by the tests”. In order to do so, he suggests the Red/Green/Refactor cycle, insisting on the 2 separated dimensions that are writing a code that works versus writing a code that is clean.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-06-30-clean-agile/clean-agile-4.png" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 100%;" /></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Simple design</strong> is the practice based on the 4 Kent Beck’s rules:
    <ul>
      <li>Pass all the tests</li>
      <li>Reveal the intent: being expressive, easy to read</li>
      <li>Remove duplication: the code shouldn’t say the same thing more than once</li>
      <li>Decrease elements (classes, functions, variables, etc)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Pair programming</strong> practice has one goal: to “share and exchange knowledge, not concentrate it”</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>As a conclusion for the book, the 4 core values of Agile are summarized :</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Courage</strong>: to say no, to rewrite code, to document well, to test well, to take a step aside, etc. “The belief that quality and discipline increase speed”</li>
  <li><strong>Communication</strong>: whatever form it takes (face-to-face, informal, interpersonal), direct and frequent communication is a must to create a team looking at the same direction</li>
  <li><strong>Feedback</strong>: giving or receiving feedback is what makes a team working efficiently</li>
  <li><strong>Simplicity</strong>: through being direct, with the idea of acknowledging a problem when you know there is one.</li>
</ul>

<p>The next pages and last chapter are designed to give ideas on how Agile values are implemented concretely ( how Agile works in small versus big companies, how to transform a non-Agile company to an Agile company, Coaching, Certification, Agile tools) as well as the next direction Uncle Bob thinks Agile should take (Synergy between Agility and Craftmanship). But for me, at this point we divert from the original purpose of this book, which is to highlight the core values of what Agility is.</p>

<p>I will thus finish this article with one of his sentences that illustrated to me his mindset while reading the book.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Agile is a small idea about the small problems of small programming teams doing small things</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Laura&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Prevost&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/laura-prevost/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;laura-prevost.jpg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Analyst&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;laura-prevost-72097255&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;laura.prevost@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Laura is an Analyst at Ordina Belgium. Also Competence Lead of Technical Leadership at Jworks. Passionate about people. Eager to share knowledge. Not afraid of challenges. Always interested in learning and discovering new things.&quot;}</name><email>laura.prevost@ordina.be</email></author><category term="Leadership" /><category term="Leadership" /><category term="Agile" /><category term="Clean" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Table of contents Introduction The Reasons for Agile Business Practices Team Practices Technical Practices Conclusion]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-06-30-clean-agile/clean_agile_home.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-06-30-clean-agile/clean_agile_home.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">RDS IAM Authentication with Spring Boot - secure password-less database authentication on AWS</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/06/13/aws-rds-iam-authentication-spring-boot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RDS IAM Authentication with Spring Boot - secure password-less database authentication on AWS" /><published>2022-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/06/13/aws-rds-iam-authentication-spring-boot</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/06/13/aws-rds-iam-authentication-spring-boot.html"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#database-role-grant">Database role grant</a></li>
  <li><a href="#aws">AWS</a></li>
  <li><a href="#spring-boot">Spring Boot</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Database authentication in Spring Boot has traditionally always been very simple to implement and configure to your needs.
Whether it is with a custom data source, or just using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">spring.datasource</code> properties, it was always pretty straightforward to get a working database connection.
Handling the sensitive data such as database passwords in different environments can be tricky, but nowadays, there are enough solutions to tackle this problem in a secure and discrete way.</p>

<p>Fortunately, if you are deploying your application on the AWS cloud, you don’t have to struggle passwords anymore or need a fancy tool, because you simply don’t need a password.
You are now able to establish a database connection by authenticating through IAM. 
Note that this feature only works for MariaDB, MySQL and PostgreSQL.</p>

<p>The feature works with “authentication tokens”, which is a string of characters that is unique and generated by Amazon RDS.
One authentication token has a lifespan of 15 minutes and needs to be re-generated before or after it expires to keep the connection alive.</p>

<p>This very useful mechanic can deeply strengthen the security of your application by erasing the need of a password and therefore, destroying another opportunity to get your sensitive data in the wrong hands.</p>

<p>Note that you need to explicitly <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonRDS/latest/UserGuide/UsingWithRDS.IAMDBAuth.Enabling.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">enable IAM authentication</a> before you can use this feature.</p>

<h2 id="database-role-grant">Database role grant</h2>
<p>Enabling IAM authentication alone is not enough.
When you create a new database user for your application, you also need to grant the rights to the database user to fetch an authentication token to use in the authentication process.</p>

<p>For Postgres, this can be done with the following SQL query:</p>
<div class="language-sql highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">CREATE</span> <span class="k">USER</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">databaseuser</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="k">WITH</span> <span class="n">LOGIN</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="k">GRANT</span> <span class="n">rds_iam</span> <span class="k">TO</span> <span class="n">databaseuser</span><span class="p">;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>For MySQL:</p>
<div class="language-sql highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">CREATE</span> <span class="k">USER</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">databaseuser</span><span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="n">IDENTIFIED</span> <span class="k">WITH</span> <span class="n">AWSAuthenticationPlugin</span> <span class="k">AS</span> <span class="s1">'RDS'</span><span class="p">;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="aws">AWS</h2>
<p>The application can only fetch a new authentication token if it has the right to do so.
Since we are running our application on an AWS environment, it only makes sense to make use of IAM roles.</p>

<div class="language-json highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
   </span><span class="nl">"Version"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"2012-10-17"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
   </span><span class="nl">"Statement"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="w">
      </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
         </span><span class="nl">"Effect"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"Allow"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
         </span><span class="nl">"Action"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="w">
             </span><span class="s2">"rds-db:connect"</span><span class="w">
         </span><span class="p">],</span><span class="w">
         </span><span class="nl">"Resource"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">[</span><span class="w">
             </span><span class="s2">"arn:aws:rds-db:region:account-id:dbuser:DbiResourceId/db-user-name"</span><span class="w">
         </span><span class="p">]</span><span class="w">
      </span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
   </span><span class="p">]</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>If you are running your application on an EC2 instance, make sure that your EC2 instance has an IAM role attached to it which explicitly gives access to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">rds-db:connect</code> action.
On EKS (Kubernetes for AWS), you can use <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/eks/latest/userguide/iam-roles-for-service-accounts.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">IAM roles for service accounts</a>.</p>

<h2 id="spring-boot">Spring Boot</h2>
<p>You will only need the <a href="https://mvnrepository.com/artifact/com.amazonaws/aws-java-sdk-rds" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">AWS SDK for RDS</a> to fetch an authentication token, which you can add as a dependency in Maven by adding the following code block:</p>

<div class="language-xml highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;dependency&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;groupId&gt;</span>com.amazonaws<span class="nt">&lt;/groupId&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;artifactId&gt;</span>aws-java-sdk-rds<span class="nt">&lt;/artifactId&gt;</span>
    <span class="nt">&lt;version&gt;</span>1.12.238<span class="nt">&lt;/version&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/dependency&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>To achieve the token fetching in Spring Boot, I created a custom <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">HikariDataSource</code> which overrides the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">getPassword()</code> method and used <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">RdsIamAuthTokenGenerator</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">GetIamAuthTokenRequest</code> to create a request for an authentication token from RDS.</p>

<div class="language-java highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="kd">public</span> <span class="kd">class</span> <span class="nc">RdsIAMDataSource</span> <span class="kd">extends</span> <span class="nc">HikariDataSource</span> <span class="o">{</span>
    <span class="nd">@Override</span>
    <span class="kd">public</span> <span class="nc">String</span> <span class="nf">getPassword</span><span class="o">()</span> <span class="o">{</span>
        <span class="nc">RdsIamAuthTokenGenerator</span> <span class="n">authTokenGenerator</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">RdsIamAuthTokenGenerator</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">builder</span><span class="o">()</span>
                <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">credentials</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">DefaultAWSCredentialsProviderChain</span><span class="o">())</span>
                <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">region</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">DefaultAwsRegionProviderChain</span><span class="o">().</span><span class="na">getRegion</span><span class="o">())</span>
                <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">build</span><span class="o">();</span>

        <span class="no">URI</span> <span class="n">jdbcUri</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">parseJdbcURL</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">getJdbcUrl</span><span class="o">());</span>

        <span class="nc">GetIamAuthTokenRequest</span> <span class="n">iamAuthTokenRequest</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">GetIamAuthTokenRequest</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">builder</span><span class="o">()</span>
                <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">hostname</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">jdbcUri</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">getHost</span><span class="o">())</span>
                <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">port</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">jdbcUri</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">getPort</span><span class="o">())</span>
                <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">userName</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">getUsername</span><span class="o">())</span>
                <span class="o">.</span><span class="na">build</span><span class="o">();</span>

        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">authTokenGenerator</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">getAuthToken</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">iamAuthTokenRequest</span><span class="o">);</span>
    <span class="o">}</span>

    <span class="kd">private</span> <span class="no">URI</span> <span class="nf">parseJdbcURL</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nc">String</span> <span class="n">jdbcUrl</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
        <span class="nc">String</span> <span class="n">uri</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">jdbcUrl</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">substring</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="o">);</span>
        <span class="k">return</span> <span class="no">URI</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="na">create</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">uri</span><span class="o">);</span>
    <span class="o">}</span>
<span class="o">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p style="text-align: center; font-style: italic;">Note that for MariaDB, you do not need your own custom implementation as <a href="https://mariadb.com/kb/en/mariadb-connector-j-250-release-notes/#aws-iam" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">they have an implementation of their own</a>.</p>

<p>To make sure that our connection does not drop due to authentication failures, we are going to set the maximum lifespan for the connection (remember that authentication tokens are only valid for 15 minutes).</p>

<p>Don’t forget to set your database properties (host, port and username). 
<strong>Important note:</strong> IAM authentication to the database requires an SSL connection.</p>

<div class="language-properties highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c"># Sets the max lifetime of each connection to 840000 ms (14 minutes). After 14 minutes, the application does a new request to RDS for a fresh authentication token
</span><span class="py">spring.datasource.hikari.max-lifetime</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">840000</span>
<span class="c"># JDBC url with the properties 'ssl' and 'sslmode', this properties are bound to PostgreSQL instances
</span><span class="py">spring.datasource.url</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">jdbc:postgresql://&lt;db-instance-name&gt;.&lt;random&gt;.&lt;region&gt;.rds.amazonaws.com:&lt;port&gt;/&lt;db-name&gt;?ssl=true&amp;sslmode=require</span>
<span class="c"># Database user which has the 'rds_iam' role
</span><span class="py">spring.datasource.username</span><span class="p">=</span><span class="s">&lt;db user&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>With this implementation, the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">getPassword()</code> method will be called every 14 minutes.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Security is an important factor in many companies and environments, and this is definitely a recommended way of securely accessing your database from inside your application as it is a big improvement over the traditional username/password authentication method.
You don’t have a password, which means you don’t have to share it, so you have zero risk of exposing your password to unwanted parties. Not having a password also eliminates the need to manage passwords and to rotate passwords every now and then.
With the authentication token lifespan of 15 minutes, each generated token is secure and expires rapidly in case the token gets leaked.</p>

<p>While it is slightly more of a hassle to set it up, it is definitely worth your while to implement RDS IAM authentication, especially if you are already running your application and infrastructure on AWS.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Yolan&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Vloeberghs&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;yolan-vloeberghs-23825aa3&quot;, &quot;github&quot;=&gt;&quot;yolanv&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/yolan-vloeberghs/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;yolan-vloeberghs.jpg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Java Consultant&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;yolan.vloeberghs@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Yolan Vloeberghs is a Java and Cloud engineer with a sharpened focus on all things related to cloud, specifically AWS. He loves to play around with various technologies and frameworks and is very passionated and eager to learn about everything related to cloud-native development.&quot;}</name><email>yolan.vloeberghs@ordina.be</email></author><category term="Cloud" /><category term="Spring Boot" /><category term="AWS" /><category term="Spring" /><category term="Security" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction Database role grant AWS Spring Boot Conclusion]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-06-13-aws-rds-iam-authentication-spring-boot.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-06-13-aws-rds-iam-authentication-spring-boot.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Connecting the Pods</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/development/2022/06/13/connecting-the-pods.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Connecting the Pods" /><published>2022-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/development/2022/06/13/connecting-the-pods</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/development/2022/06/13/connecting-the-pods.html"><![CDATA[<p>Although I finished the book “<a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Connected-Company-Dave-Gray/dp/1491919477/ref=sr_1_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Connected Company</a>” several months ago, I only recently got around to gathering my thoughts on the matter and putting them to paper. 
The book itself came out in 2012, which at this point is already 10 years in the past, and it largely builds on the idea of the quantum organization (Ralph Kilmann), on which I already briefly extrapolated when I wrote about <a href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/architecture/2020/07/08/Book-Five-Dysfunctions.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the Five Dysfunctions of a Team</a>.</p>

<p>The book consists of 5 parts:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Why change? The drivers behind the move towards a Connected Company.</li>
  <li>What is a Connected Company? The book offers an attempt at a definition and the listing of the characteristics of such a company.</li>
  <li>How does a Connected Company work? The adapted processes and organizational impacts on the company are reviewed in this part.</li>
  <li>How do you lead a Connected Company? The hierarchy (and/or lack thereof) of this new type of company.</li>
  <li>How do you get there from here? The evolution that the organization needs to go through in order to claim the vaunted title.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="part-1-why-change">Part 1: Why Change?</h2>

<p>The first part aims to explain the different drivers that make the transition to a Connected Company necessary. 
The idea is to have an abstraction derived from several customer cases. 
The first chapters go about comparing the organization to a network, where significant events can travel the different nodes of a network and have an impact on all of them. 
The organization of today is a participant in a multitude of social networks (employees, customers, competitors, shareholders…), and each of these shapes how the power balance within the organization is established.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/networkanatomy.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>Traditional companies have an information stream that is pretty much one direction. 
The company would have an unending stream of products that would be shipped out to customers, and so the company is organized and optimized for such an exchange. 
However, this industrial age has given way to a situation where the feedback from these customers will change how the company goes about things and forces companies to create customer relationships where they will have to listen to these customers. 
This service economy necessitates new habits, behaviors, and organizational structures.</p>

<p>The author states that the change towards this service economy is supported by three factors: product saturation, information technology, and urbanization. 
There are some issues with this analysis as far as I’m concerned. 
Or rather some tweaks I would add with the benefit of ten years of hindsight. 
While product saturation is indeed present in most industries, the notion that Customer Intimacy will always be victorious over Product Leadership or Operational Excellence seems a bit curt. 
I would half expect Customer Intimacy to work better in a blue-ocean-type of industry where the saturation has not yet peaked. 
As for urbanization, this is a concept I would switch out for globalization with the social networks of the internet generating a much greater impact. 
Information technology is then just an extension of this globalization, making such social networks possible.</p>

<p>Around the time of this book’s release, there was similarly the notion of Social Business Process Management rearing its head. 
Social BPM refers to a twofold mindset. 
On the one hand, it uses Web 2.0 and Enterprise 2.0 style collaboration portals where participants can share and influence process design and certain decision-making activities during process execution. 
On the other hand, we also speak of Social BPM when we allude to leveraging the organization’s outward social media resources into internal business processes.</p>

<p>In 2014 Gartner had retitled the first of the mindsets as Design-By-Doing BPM, as placed it thus named on its Hype Cycle, as seen in the illustration below. 
While supported by advanced BPM technology and social software in order to make process design more visible and holistic (thus guaranteeing the “emergent” design), it also requires a user experience perspective and their willingness to step into such an endeavor so that social networks of employees can be cultivated and mobilized around the idea of bottom-up process improvement efforts.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/gartnersocialbpm.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>The critical difference between services and products is this more direct co-creation with the customer. 
They decide where, when, and how the services are delivered. 
This makes services highly contextual and places the value of services to the customer in the interaction (or customer experience). 
To draw the similarities with the social web even further: Products can then be considered the end result of a service to the customer and become the physical manifestation or avatar of the service.</p>

<p>It seems like common sense to care about and keep track of customers. 
But when companies start to grow, a lot of distractions have a way of muddying the waters with other preoccupations, resulting in a decline in customer focus. 
These distractions can range from a multitude of new opportunities to internal efficiency drives, over-expansion (with product dilution as a result), and so on. 
This can also lead to an automation of processes to handle the increasing complexity with the caveat of these automations becoming too restrictive, and limiting the creativity and adaptability of your services. 
Where the author argues this case, I would however stipulate that over-automation is easily mitigated by determining which of your processes are run-of-the-mill and which add value to your unique selling point or differentiator. 
The former are ideal candidates for such an automation drive (or standardization) whereas the latter are more suited for custom development that allows for easy adaptation. 
This comes down to finding a balance between efficiency and adaptability/innovation.</p>

<p>Another game changer is the number of companies that go belly up. 
This is largely due to the complexity of the market increasing, with new technologies popping up all over and disrupting the market in addition to the previously mentioned globalization which increases the number of competitors companies have to deal with. 
This might have seemed like a new reality, but remember the phrase “Innovate or Die” by Peter Drucker who was already advocating such disruptions back in 1985. 
According to the author, the solution to this disruption is the Coevolutionary Process. 
Every time you adapt, the others in your industry are forced to do so as well and vice versa. 
This process can be competitive, but also cooperative with tactical alliances giving your company the leg up it needs to stay ahead of the rat race. 
There are other <a href="https://evolute.be/thoughts/disruption.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">forms of disruption</a>, but these are what the author wishes to focus on.</p>

<h2 id="part-2-what-is-a-connected-company">Part 2: What is a Connected Company?</h2>

<p>Companies must stop acting like machines, but should behave as learning organisms who interact with their environment and improve based on experiments and feedback. 
This is the premise of the author and reminiscent of the argumentation of Friedrich August von Hayek, renowned economist and contemporary (although in theories diametrically opposed) to John Meynard Keynes. 
F. A. Hayek would go on record stating the economy is organic, not like a well-oiled machine that can be fixed as stipulated by Keynes.</p>

<p>The comparison of a company to a machine comes from the scientific management theory of Frederick Taylor and has helped some of the great industry giants get to where they were at the pinnacle of their profit. 
Knowledge is explicit and absolute and can be represented in operating manuals, documentation, and metrics. 
These “machines” have the following characteristics:</p>
<ol>
  <li>The machine needs to be controlled by an operator or driver.</li>
  <li>It needs to be maintained, and when it breaks down, you fix it.</li>
  <li>A machine works the same way its entire life, and when it is no longer useful, you build a new one.</li>
</ol>

<p>I do not think this comparison holds up to a company, but arguments can be made to equate it to value chains or processes within a company. 
This static nature of the process will come into conflict with the changes all around us, and we need mechanisms to deal with this change. 
It will also clash with people’s inherent resistance to being controlled. 
The author will propose the Connected Company approach for this.</p>

<p>Where the Connected Company wants to make a paradigm shift, is to move the focus from procedures and rules where there is the idea of an optimal solution that balances the needs of the company with those of the customers towards a company putting the focus more on the customer and to become more like a support system for those customers. 
Ashby’s Law (also called the Law of Requisite Variety) is mentioned in one breath with this view: Any control system must be capable of variety that is greater or equal to the variety in the system to be controlled. 
However, this seems to assume that processes within companies are fixed, while the whole discipline of Business Process Management is predicated on the fact that a process is never finished, and that there is always room for improvement, either induced by internal or external factors.</p>

<p>In any case, a case is made for customers resisting standardization, and that to meet such required variety, the company needs innovation. 
One of those ways to achieve this is to give the employees of the company the freedom to experiment. 
This also benefits the employees in their learning, which is fundamentally different from receiving training. 
Learning is a way to deal with new situations, and how an employee deals with the uncertainties that might be encountered.</p>

<p>It is also quite comical to see that the author later on in the chapters talks of the Net Promoter Score (NPS) as a way to track customer satisfaction as if the NPS is not a metric. 
NPS is a score that attempts to measure the customer perception of the company by asking the customers to rate it on a scale of 1 to 10. 
This puts each customer in one of three categories based on the score they gave:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Promoters: The most avid fans of your services. These customers will regularly buy your products or services and recommend them to others.</li>
  <li>Passives: Customers that are willing to shift to one of your competitors if a better deal comes along.</li>
  <li>Detractors: These are the malcontent customers that might even dissuade others from buying your product or services.</li>
</ul>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/NPS.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>Your overall company NPS equals the percentage of protomers reduced by the number of detractors.</p>

<p>Going on the findings from <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Living-Company-Learning-Longevity-Business-ebook/dp/B01HPVHKPO/ref=sr_1_" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Living Company</a> by Arie De Geus, companies that stand the test of time share certain similarities:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Distributed Control: The company should be decentralized and connected to a wide array of partners.</li>
  <li>Strong Identity: Although the organizational structure was loosely coupled, the company culture was known and carried by all employees.</li>
  <li>Feedback Loops: Companies should take their cue from the world they inhabit, reacting to feedback and improving their workings based on it.</li>
</ul>

<p>In essence, companies should move from a design by division to a design for connection. 
It should not be defined by its individual pieces within its own borders, but rather by the partnership it can form and the information it can extract from these partnerships, be they with customers, suppliers, strategic partners, or even competitors.</p>

<p>While it is important for companies to turn a profit, there are good profits and bad profits. 
This is one of the purposes of a company, much like proving to be a worthy investment for shareholders and providing a livelihood for its employees. 
Good profits are derived from creating value for your customers. 
Bad profits are those made at the expense of the happiness of customers, prioritizing the maximization of short-term profit over long-term sustainability. 
While this type of profit maximization might be to the benefit of the stakeholders, the other parties (customers and employees) will feel the backlash. 
All in all, the company should put maximum effort into aligning its performance to what it promised, and furthermore aligning that promise to what customers actually need or want (purpose). 
This balancing exercise will aid tremendously in veering towards good profits. 
This can once again be mapped to the 3 categories of business strategy: Customer Intimacy, Product Leadership, and Operational Excellence.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/strategies.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<h2 id="part-3-how-does-a-connected-company-work">Part 3: How does a Connected Company work?</h2>

<p>Business agility is the name of the game and the Connected Company tries to address this topic through the standard technological ways that are available in an attempt to make the company more built for agility:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Agile Development with small autonomous teams</li>
  <li>Service Oriented Development with service contracts, a focus on composability, and loose coupling</li>
</ul>

<p>The idea is to transform a business into a podular organization. 
This is an approach that combines the traditional organization split into divisions with pods where you divide the required work into “businesses within businesses”, which can function independently from other pods, and take on the responsibility for a complete “service”. 
This allows the organization to represent itself as a group of smaller organizations. 
Each of these pods is autonomous and can function on behalf of the business as a whole.</p>

<p>In a traditional company with divisions, the need for a Corporate Strategy occurs when an enterprise develops multiple divisions (typically linked to separate value chains), each with a distinct business strategy. 
This is for example the case when a company starts diversifying its products or services. 
Based on how the corporate strategy is handled across these divisions, we can segment the types of diversification into 4 main categories. 
Single Businesses are centralized and can be defined as having a predominant business strategy that applies to almost all of their business units. 
Dominant Businesses still have business strategies that vary and take up a significant part of the enterprise, but overall they follow one centralized strategy that accounts for most of their enterprise. 
Next, we have the diversified businesses, which are comprised of several business strategies, be they related to each other (for example they are all still targeting the technological markets) and thus able to share a value chain, or be they completely unrelated (typically conglomerates). 
The podular organization attempts to take this conglomerate idea to the next level, and apply it within individual divisions.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/strategies02.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>So what is a pod? 
A small, autonomous unit that has the mandate and the capabilities to deliver whatever it is that its customers value. 
It is designed to take decisions and implement changes as quickly and as close to the customer as possible. 
Whereas the traditional company employs processes that can be seen as recipes or a series of steps that need to be executed, the podular organization is structured as a net, distributing the workload based on goals instead of allocating individual steps or stages. 
And the pods are not necessarily part of the same organization or company but could extend across several to couple its inherent benefits with more economy-of-scale oriented benefits.</p>

<p>This gives a number of advantages based on its lattice-like structure, exchanging consistency and efficiency for flexibility and creativity:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Pods are flexible: changing the structure and purpose is easy and fast.</li>
  <li>Pods are allowed to fail as the network will provide redundancy by adjusting the purpose of similar pods.</li>
  <li>Pods can scale up fast by adding additional pods and letting them immediately contribute.</li>
</ul>

<p>This type of flexibility cannot exist in a vacuum. 
It needs a proper support system (or platform) to make it happen, necessitating a shared infrastructure for all available and future pods, such as for example a proper cloud adoption. 
Although it might seem quite a daunting task to put in place, this shared infrastructure offers numerous benefits:</p>
<ul>
  <li>More traffic brings more customers and in turn more business.</li>
  <li>It allows for a focus on differentiators, making it possible to prioritize certain services and products that are “hot” at the moment, only to switch to others when the need arises.</li>
  <li>The commonality between these pods (common technological standards and shared company culture) generates trust with customers who can see a rise in the overall quality of all services and products offered.</li>
</ul>

<p>As with all organizations, the connected company needs to continue to evolve. 
This is done by learning, and the connected company sees learning as a growth spiral called successive approximation. 
The connected company takes actions, which leads to feedback and discovery based on the outcome of such actions. 
Once these are collected, you reflect upon how to change the way actions are taken to improve their result. 
When compared to more traditional ways of learning such as the Double-Loop Learning, to me, this seems like the reflection part is portrayed as a bit too straightforward. 
If the results of your actions are the only thing to reflect upon, the reframing of the mindset is missed.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/learning.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>To go a bit more into detail on this type of learning: Professor Chris Argyris of Harvard Business School identifies three possible levels of learning in an organization, which he coined single-loop, double-loop, and deutero learning. 
The idea is that with single-loop learning we adjust the capability so that variances in results are addressed. 
We can look at this as attacking the symptoms of a supply chain problem. 
With double-loop learning, we search for the under-lying reason for the symptoms of a problem and try to remedy this reason in order to make sure the symptoms no longer occur. 
One might conclude that double-loop learning is a sounder strategy for attacking problems, but this is incorrect. 
Both are needed for a balanced resolution of the issues with a supply chain. 
Take for instance the occurrence of a fire. 
One needs to address putting out the flames (symptom) before being able to tackle the underlying reason. 
The balanced application of both of these levels is called deutero learning, which is the preferred manner of proceeding.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/deutero.png" alt="Workspace" class="image fit" style="margin:0px auto; max-width:100%" /></p>

<p>The successive approximation approach in the book focuses on three levels of learning: 
How entrepreneurs learn, how companies learn, and how the platform learns.</p>

<p>The entrepreneurial method for learning (as stated by Saras Sarasvathy) states that entrepreneurs focus on the qualities they possess within the organization and attempt to utilize these to their greatest effect. 
This translates into the following points:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Entrepreneurs do not start with predictions, but rather with their cares, experiences, and network of people. The learning is based on interactions with people, trying things out on a small scale, and asking questions.</li>
  <li>Entrepreneurs seek commitment from the people in their projects.</li>
  <li>With the commitment of people to projects, these projects gain momentum, new capabilities, and an expanding roster of committed people. This reflects on the projects through realigning the goals with their new reality.</li>
  <li>With the accumulation of resources, the project coalesces in a working model typically coupled with a new and innovative offering.</li>
</ol>

<p>Organizations learn through two distinct flows. 
Tacit Knowledge is the knowledge that is being picked up through doing. Experience in the truest sense. 
Explicit Knowledge is the knowledge that is being shared, measured, and documented… 
Both are valuable and the organization needs to come up with ways to combine these for maximum effect, for example installing learning spaces where colleagues can come together and share their experiences to achieve the desired cross-pollination.</p>

<p>How platforms learn is likened to the Pace Layered Architecture that was popularized amongst others by Gartner. 
I have already given my views on this in a previous blogpost: <a href="https://evolute.be/thoughts/anyroad.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Any Road Will Get You There</a></p>

<h2 id="part-4-how-do-you-lead-a-connected-company">Part 4: How Do You Lead a Connected Company?</h2>

<p>The book states that strategy happens at all levels, but instead of a corporate strategy filtering down to the business units that make up the company, it should be more like a pool of experiments at all levels from which senior management can cherry-pick to achieve success. 
This would seem to me to imply that there is a definite risk of squandering opportunities where the opportunity cost far outweighs the benefits such experimenting brings with it. 
On the other hand, this will help innovation tremendously with the possibility of higher returns. 
So this would be a high-risk high rewards type of situation much in line with blue ocean strategic thinking. 
It shifts strategy from being driven by prediction to being driven by discovery. 
This is referenced by the book as the content of Eric D. Beinhocker’s book “<a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Origin-Wealth-Evolution-Complexity-Economics/dp/0712676619/ref=sr_1_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Origin of Wealth</a>”, where he labels these two strategic approaches as deliberate and emergent strategy.</p>

<p>Another view on strategic approaches comes from colonel John Boyd, whose OODA loop formed the inspiration for the previously mentioned double-loop learning. 
He states three facets of conflict (or in our case competition with rivaling companies): attrition warfare, maneuver warfare, and moral warfare.</p>

<p>Attrition warfare is when companies will invest huge capital to corner the market and push out competitors. 
This will work in certain scenarios. 
Typically in saturated markets where the only discriminator will be price, such tactics can yield the desired result. 
But this is an expensive proposition.</p>

<p>Maneuver warfare focuses on new technologies to leverage them in the same way cash is used with attrition warfare. 
To translate this concept to the Connected Company, it needs an emphasis on learning and adapting to new technologies to faster seize opportunities, and as such maximize your advantage in the market. 
The more you distribute control, the faster you can learn and “maneuver”.</p>

<p>The last of these is moral warfare where you play on the minds and emotions of the customer base while vilifying your competitors. 
The greater your moral authority, the more cohesive your company culture and your people are, and the greater the impact they can deliver. 
In essence, think people first! Attracting the good and competent people, keeping them, and elevating their worth through learning, gives your company a head start in the competition race.</p>

<p>Management in the end comes down to having a single purpose for the organization: To design, run and continuously improve the systems that enable it to effectively pursue its goals. 
A shift needs to be created in traditional management from organizing and supervising (or the well-known command and control management style) to a management that is focused on support (what we label servant leadership) with the previous style on the backburner. 
Flexibility and structure must be balanced so that the system has enough formalized structure to avoid endlessly reinventing and repeating routine work, and enough adaptability and freedom to not overly constrain work and creativity. 
This balance is denoted by the so-called tipping points or critical values in your complex adaptive system. 
Once your cadence moves past such a tipping point, the dynamic of your workforce and productivity shifts, and needs addressing. 
This is called “tuning the system”, and aims at keeping the organization in the goldilocks zone of that balance.</p>

<p>In order to apply all of these strategic and management concepts, a company needs to have the proper tools in the organizational toolbelt. 
These are such tools as situational awareness (sensing and understanding the context of its ecosystem to judge changes and their potential impact), dealing with adaptive tensions that are constantly happening in its ecosystem, information transparency (with Lord Kelvin’s “measuring is knowing” adage), and diversification both in terms of products and services as well as people to ensure the company can evolve. 
The book also mentions command intent, a term used in the military to depict a common goal to work towards. 
For companies, this becomes a broad vision that leaves the individual pods a large degree of freedom in how to put plans into action (leaning back to the principles of deliberate strategy).</p>

<h2 id="part-5-how-do-you-get-there-from-here">Part 5: How do you get there from here?</h2>

<p>The final part of the book is the smallest by far, a mere 25 pages. 
It deals with what to do to transform your organization into the podular variety, and what risks might be associated with such a transformation. 
This change can be kickstarted in four distinct ways: organic growth, top-down leader-driven change, pilot pods, and network weaving.</p>

<p>The organic growth of a company happens when it starts as a small entity and slowly builds itself up. 
Typically you will find small teams in such a startup that are acting in a similar manner to the pods in the podular organization. 
The focus, in this case, should be on a shared purpose, let autonomous pods spring to life naturally, and create additional growth through replicating pods by moving people already familiar with the workings of pods into the newly created ones.</p>

<p>Top-down leader-driven change is a more difficult path that demands commitment from the company leadership to steer it in this new direction. 
There are certain themes that need to be incorporated into this type of change, notably: a focus on customers, avoidance of abundant bureaucracy, moving the decisions closer to where the customers interact with the company, fostering teamwork, and putting your people first as they are the ones that will need to make the pods successful.</p>

<p>Pilot pods are proof-of-concept style pods that can be used to feel things out on how to proceed with this change. 
They are useful to gather experience and find the proper balances that need to be struck in strategy and execution. 
These will be outside of typical company structures and should therefore have enough leeway to figure out whether they will be successful, and not be written off at the first signs of trouble.</p>

<p>Network weaving is the last way to get your company on the podular bandwagon. 
By forging better networks and more connections, the company becomes more effective and adaptive, as there is a cross-pollination that will deliver the needed expertise and knowledge workers that can precipitate the change. 
This is however the slow-burn step-by-step approach and will require more time than the previous options to become a full-fledged podular entity.</p>

<p>The journey can be perilous, and there are risks that can be expected in the form of failures. 
With this type of transformation, these risks should be mitigated as soon as possible when they present themselves. 
The failures can happen at different levels:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Failure at the pod level: The distribution of control is very important. As stated earlier in this post, the balance between deliberate and strategic management determines the proper strategy. The level of autonomy given to each pod is an equally important equilibrium. Too much autonomy for any pod can become a liability for the company and severely limit the ability of other pods to function properly. Too little autonomy will infringe upon the pods’ creativity and the ability to learn. This is a fine line that can only be pinpointed through adequate preparation and trial runs.</li>
  <li>Failure at the platform level: As the platform is needed to allow for this podular way of working, there are certain requirements attached to such a support system: The proper amount of investment needs to be made to have a platform that will suit the needs of this type of organization. There is also the same danger at this level as was in the previous: The danger of over-controlling the platform, or making the barriers to entry too strong by asking too much in return for using the platform (be it conditions or cost or any other quid pro quo). There should be a burden shared by all participants, but this should not outweigh the benefits.</li>
  <li>Failure of purpose: The focus should remain on the vision of the company, and not just focused on turning a profit. This can lead too easily to the disintegration of the overall company culture as pods migrate further and further away from each other in the pursuit of the bottom line.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I found the book to be written in a straightforward but not very deep-delving way. 
As such I would recommend it for non-business-minded consultants to have an introduction to this subject matter, “For Dummies”-style. 
It is a starting point to get the general frame of mind before delving deeper into organizational concepts, business strategy, and other related areas. 
It does a good job of lifting the veil enough to get newcomers excited about what else is out there to be learned.</p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Peter&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;De Kinder&quot;, &quot;github&quot;=&gt;&quot;peterdekinder&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;peterdekinder&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/peterdekinder/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;peterdekinder.jpg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Solution Architect&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;peter.dekinder@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Peter is a Solution Architect with firm roots in the Java technosphere, but with a wide interest in all things architecture. His areas of specialization include Service Oriented Architectures, Business Process Management and Security.&quot;}</name><email>peter.dekinder@ordina.be</email></author><category term="development" /><category term="technical leadership" /><category term="architecture" /><category term="software architecture" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Although I finished the book “The Connected Company” several months ago, I only recently got around to gathering my thoughts on the matter and putting them to paper. The book itself came out in 2012, which at this point is already 10 years in the past, and it largely builds on the idea of the quantum organization (Ralph Kilmann), on which I already briefly extrapolated when I wrote about the Five Dysfunctions of a Team.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/tile.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-06-13-connecting-the-pods/tile.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">JWorks @ KubeCon 2022</title><link href="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/06/10/kubecon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="JWorks @ KubeCon 2022" /><published>2022-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/06/10/kubecon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/cloud/2022/06/10/kubecon.html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>KubeCon - CloudNativeCon - JWorks was there!</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h1>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#key-takeaways">Key takeaways</a></li>
  <li><a href="#meet-the-vendors">Meet the vendors</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>KubeCon | CloudNativeCon is a conference organised by the Cloud Native Computing Foundation twice a year, alternating between Europe and US locations. 
This edition took place in Valencia in Spain. 
The conference is the industry conference for anything Kubernetes and container-related technology. 
Talks range from end-user stories of the usage of Kubernetes, over methods to automate compliance in Cloud to technical deep dives into specific cloud-native building blocks.
Next to the talks, there’s a solution exhibition as well.
This is where vendors and (CNCF) projects have booths and you can talk to core contributors of most of the projects.</p>

<h2 id="key-takeaways">Key takeaways</h2>

<h3 id="opentelemetry">OpenTelemetry</h3>
<p>OpenTelemetry is a CNCF project focused on capturing different telemetry signals from applications.
It’s a collection of tools, SDKs and APIs that enable effective observability.</p>

<p>In essence, it’s an ecosystem of tools that can instrument, capture and ship (currently) telemetry data to different systems. 
The idea is that the tooling to do so is provided by OpenTelemetry and the analysis, usage and storage are performed by other third-party tools like Dynatrace, AWS X-Ray, Elastic, Grafana LGTM or any other tool supporting telemetry data.</p>

<h3 id="supply-chain-security">Supply chain security</h3>
<p>This was more of a general topic than a specific product or talk. 
During one of the keynotes, it was mentioned that there is a clear increase in software supply chain attacks from multiple vectors. 
Multiple talks discussed how provenance could be used to determine if an image is safe to run aka went through all the necessary steps to end where it’s being deployed.
Especially the talk <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Q-ZeN6WXg8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fun with Continuous Compliance</a> by Ann Wallace and Zeal Somani of Shopify and Google provides an introduction into how that could work and showcases how Shopify has this setup in their environment. 
It also showcases how you can link compliance evidence gathered from your systems directly into audit reports using the OSCAL standard.</p>

<h3 id="nats">NATS</h3>
<p>Back in 2019, one the hottest topics of KubeCon (North America) was the introduction of NATS. Now, 3 years later it seemed to have gained a lot of popularity. Most of the interesting projects that where presented during talks used NATS for communication between their distributed microservice architectures.</p>

<p>NATS is an infrastructure is a message oriented middleware that allows applications to store and distribute data in realtime in a general manner across various environments, langauges, cloud providers and on-premises systems.</p>

<h3 id="agua-de-valencia">Agua de Valencia</h3>
<p>Agua de Valencia is not water from the city of Valencia as the name suggests it to be, but rather a different drink. The main thing that can’t be ignored from the Valencian scenery is its orange trees. The juice of these oranges forms the base of Agua de Valencia. Agua de Valencia is a cocktail containing orange juice, cava (the Spanish interpretation of champagne), gin, vodka and sugar, and it turns out to taste very nice in combination with Tapas after a long day of KubeCon.</p>

<p><img class="image left" src="/img/2022-05-20-kubecon/aqua1.jpg" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" />
<img class="image right" src="/img/2022-05-20-kubecon/aqua2.jpg" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<h2 id="meet-the-vendors">Meet the vendors</h2>

<h3 id="castai-cost-optimization">Cast.ai cost optimization</h3>
<p>We met Cast.ai at their booth because we were triggered by the slogan “half your cloud cost”. 
Cast.ai is a SaaS solution aimed at reducing the cost of a Kubernetes setup by performing multiple (AI-based) optimizations. 
They work by installing an agent into your cluster and analysing all workloads that are deployed.
Next, they provide a detailed report of the improvements you can make.
Their main approach is two-fold.</p>

<h4 id="rightsizing">Rightsizing</h4>
<p>Based on the analysis of all workloads, Cast.ai will provide a suggestion with nodes that are sized just right for the workloads on your cluster.
Instead of using just a single VM type per node pool, they look at the workloads and which nodes would be the most cost-effective. 
Since this approach optimizes for the CPU, memory and storage requests in your cluster at a moment in time, you’ll have to set them correctly as well.</p>

<h4 id="spot-instances">Spot instances</h4>
<p>The second suggestion or approach they have is the usage of spot instances. 
When spot capacity is available in your selected regions, they will spot instances and attach them to your cluster.
Since spot instances are vastly cheaper, this can generate up to 60% in savings. 
One of the requirements for this approach to work is that either all workloads have multiple replicas, or the cluster can sustain some workload downtime (e.g. integration cluster, some development cluster, …).</p>

<h3 id="vmware-tanzu">VMWare Tanzu</h3>
<p>VMWare was present with their Tanzu team. 
They showcased how Tanzu solves the software supply chain challenges using open-source software. 
Ranging from tooling to support an in-house training self-service portal to the native building of images using Contour (CI) and KPack (Tanzu Build service) to managing large fleets of Kubernetes clusters across multiple (public) cloud providers, VMWare Tanzu solves all of it for you.</p>

<h2 id="meet-the-city-valencia">Meet the city: Valencia</h2>
<p>Of course, we also explored the city of Valencia during the hours that the conference was not in session. 
We can recommend having drinks at the bar in the Mercat de Colón. 
The city center has good tapas throughout and especially if you go to the Ruzafa district, we can recommend <a href="https://g.page/Trufasalvajevalencia?share" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Trufa Salvaje</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>It was clear that no expense was saved by vendors to make their products visible to people joining KubeCon.
Portworx advertised “the old way” by buying ad space on old fashioned billboards next to the highway to the conference center and decals on the city metros.
Gitlab had bought what seemed like all the advertisement space in the airport. 
It was amazing, crazy and weird at the same time to realize that those ads were there specifically to target people going to the conference.</p>

<p><img class="image left" src="/img/2022-05-20-kubecon/ad2.jpg" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" />
<img class="image right" src="/img/2022-05-20-kubecon/ad3.jpeg" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 50%;" /></p>

<p>To us, there was a clear focus throughout the conference on three topics: Supply chain security, observability and FinOps. 
Both in the talks and the vendor area, it is clear that these topics are hot and a lot of companies are working on improving these spaces.</p>

<p>The most exciting CNCF project to watch in the next 12 months is OpenTelemetry for sure. 
They have a lot of traction in the community and seem to become the defacto standard for shipping any observability signals.</p>

<p>Finally, the most important takeaway from this conference is that being together as a community again is the best thing ever.
Talking with co-workers about talks over drinks, talking directly to maintainers of projects you only knew by their Github or Slack handle previously and connecting with vendors that solve problems you didn’t even know you had, is simply priceless. 
Our team came back from this conference full of new ideas on how to improve our different projects and how to support customer use cases even better in the future. 
Connections with key people at vendors and open source projects have been made which make reaching out and discussing things in the future a lot easier.</p>

<h3 id="tldr-good-talks-to-watch">TLDR; Good talks to watch</h3>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eM3RXdK1yys" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Prometheus intro</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qE1ggEmvz2Y" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OpenTelemetry intro</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FQucIjAqZrY" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Community Manager talk</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9tYkxlhXdw4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ArgoCD overview</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xDGjmav8UBg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Good public post-mortem</a></li>
</ul>

<p><strong><em>“Great things in business are never done by one person. They are done by a team of people”</em>.</strong> –&gt;
<img class="image fit" src="/img/2022-05-20-kubecon/go-team.jpg" style="margin:0px auto; max-width: 100%;" /></p>]]></content><author><name>{&quot;first_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Pieter&quot;, &quot;last_name&quot;=&gt;&quot;Vincken&quot;, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;&quot;pieter-vincken-a94b5153&quot;, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;PieterVincken&quot;, &quot;github&quot;=&gt;&quot;pietervincken&quot;, &quot;permalink&quot;=&gt;&quot;/author/pieter_vincken/&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;pieter-vincken.jpeg&quot;, &quot;title&quot;=&gt;&quot;Cloud Automation Engineer&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;pieter.vincken@ordina.be&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Pieter Vincken is a Cloud Automation Engineer with a strong interest in anything related to Cloud Native. He likes to optimize development workflows, from Ideation until code running in production, by enabling CI/CD to be fully automated. Any solutions he creates, will have started as an architectural drawing.&quot;}</name><email>pieter.vincken@ordina.be</email></author><category term="Cloud" /><category term="Cloud" /><category term="Cloud-Native" /><category term="Conference" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[KubeCon - CloudNativeCon - JWorks was there!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-05-20-kubecon/kccnc-eu-2022-color-resized.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://ordina-jworks.github.io/img/2022-05-20-kubecon/kccnc-eu-2022-color-resized.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>